<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Painting on Varun Mangalick</title>
    <link>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Painting on Varun Mangalick</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 20:16:25 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://example.org/hobbies/painting/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Painting: the paint wall</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-3-paint-wall/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 20:16:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-3-paint-wall/</guid>
      <description>In January 2022, one of my cousins gave me some extra paints her kids weren&amp;rsquo;t using, which ended up spawning 15+ paint nights over the course of over a year. Things slowed down a bit in 2023, but even so, these paintings formed a giant mosiac paint wall in the living room of my apartment.
Overall, I&amp;rsquo;m up to 57 total paintings (2 not pictured as they&amp;rsquo;re on the second wall) from 20+ people.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In January 2022, one of my cousins gave me some extra paints her kids weren&rsquo;t using, which ended up spawning 15+ paint nights over the course of over a year. Things slowed down a bit in 2023, but even so, these paintings formed a giant mosiac paint wall in the living room of my apartment.</p>
<p>Overall, I&rsquo;m up to 57 total paintings (2 not pictured as they&rsquo;re on the second wall) from 20+ people. I&rsquo;ve told people they&rsquo;re free to take paintings home, but that they should leave the first one here and come back for it when they paint the second one. This strategy has been successful in having every single painting left here as part of the paint wall.</p>
<p>When people join for paint night, it&rsquo;s pretty unstructured, so everyone can paint what they&rsquo;d like, whether that means following a video, using a picture, or just painting from imagination. As a result, we have a fantastic diversity of subjects and styles! There was only one paint night where multiple people followed the same video, though I did my best to arrange those three paintings far from each other. See if you can spot them!</p>
<p>One of my favorite paintings I&rsquo;ve done is Ocean in a Drop. I started by following a tutorial on painting a water drop, then added a whale along with a school of small red fish. One detail that really helped with the sense of realism was adding slightly offset shadows to the creatures. I posted it <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/painting/comments/uqklix/drop_of_ocean_me_acrylics_on_loose_canvas/">on reddit</a> and got a surprisingly positive reception!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/ocean_drop.jpg" type="" alt="Ocean in a water drop painting"  /></p>
<p>Another favorite is Propaganda Poster of a Plush Dino. I hadn&rsquo;t actually done any dinosaur paintings on this paint wall, so I thought I might as well revisit the old favorite subject. I tried to make the dinosaur fuzzy and 3d to contrast from the bright and flat colors in the background. After painting this, I enjoyed looking back at my 3d dino from <a href="http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-1-dinos/">my freshman summer series</a> and seeing how much I improved on shading since then!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/propaganda_dino.jpg" type="" alt="Propaganda poster of a plush dino painting"  /></p>
<p>COMING SOON: I&rsquo;m going to try to make an interactive version of the paint wall where you can hover over individual paintings and see a blown up image + artist creds. I&rsquo;ll likely publish this as a separate post!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Painting: a dinosaur through the eye of Chuck Close</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-2-big-dino/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2018 11:23:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-2-big-dino/</guid>
      <description>At the start of my college junior summer, I painted what is still probably my single favorite thing I&amp;rsquo;ve painted. I was staying with my aunt for a couple days before starting my internship, and I took the opportunity to paint with my artist cousin Sonika didi. She&amp;rsquo;s absolutely fantastic and paints pieces for galleries while also working in art education. See her pieces here!
We looked at a variety of modern artists to get style inspiration, and ended up settling on Chuck Close.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>At the start of my college junior summer, I painted what is still probably my single favorite thing I&rsquo;ve painted. I was staying with my aunt for a couple days before starting my internship, and I took the opportunity to paint with my artist cousin Sonika didi. She&rsquo;s absolutely fantastic and paints pieces for galleries while also working in art education. See her pieces <a href="https://www.instagram.com/sonikart13/">here</a>!</p>
<p>We looked at a variety of modern artists to get style inspiration, and ended up settling on Chuck Close. We didn&rsquo;t feel we could quite capture the surprising level of realism he managed to achieve, but it would be fun to try painting with a diagonal grid texture anyways. I was very happy with how mine ended up turning out! I had lots of fun altering the shades of the individual cells on both the background and dinosaur to indicate the light source being present on the top right of the painting. Sonika didi&rsquo;s cat was also really cool!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/cat.jpg" type="" alt="Sonika didi&amp;rsquo;s painting of a Chuck Close style cat"  /></p>
<p>A few months later when I had returned to school for the fall semester, a new student lounge on campus (the Banana Lounge) put out a call for student art. I submitted a pic of my dinosaur and had it accepted! I was sad to have it leave my dorm room, but I was so excited for a chance to have something I created be on display for others to see.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/lounge_dino.jpg" type="" alt="Big dino painting in MIT"  /></p>
<p>To make up for the loss of my painting from my room, one of my cousins Avni recommended printing custom stickers, which I ended up putting on my water bottle and laptop and giving to various friends. The below picture shows a great example of a mint condition one I put in on my new laptop in mid 2023 vs a well-loved one that had lived on my water bottle in early 2019.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/dino_sticker.jpg" type="" alt="A tale of two stickers: mint vs well loved"  /></p>
<p>I graduated college, moved to NYC for a job, moved back to MN for covid lockdown, got a new job in Boston and moved there, and finally realized, once the current crop of seniors graduated from MIT, I&rsquo;d lose personal connection to the banana lounge team and potentially lose the ability to reclaim my painting.</p>
<p>Thankfully, one of the coordinators of the space, Zoe, had been a freshman on my floor when I was a senior, so I was able to reach out to her and get my painting back. Coincidentally, my work asked for office art around this time, so my painting went straight from MIT to Reverie Labs!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Painting: a series of dinosaurs</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-1-dinos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 21:19:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-1-dinos/</guid>
      <description>During my college freshman summer when I was doing my first internship. I bought paints to have something to do after work, as this was the first time in my life I didn&amp;rsquo;t have homework. This summer, I painted several simple dinosaur paintings!
So why dinosaurs? As a kid, I was obsessed with dinosaurs, and this aspect is something most people still associate with me. I didn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily feel like I HAD to only paint dinosaurs, but they felt like a reasonable default subject to use to practice different styles.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>During my college freshman summer when I was doing my first internship. I bought paints to have something to do after work, as this was the first time in my life I didn&rsquo;t have homework. This summer, I painted several simple dinosaur paintings!</p>
<p>So why dinosaurs? As a kid, I was obsessed with dinosaurs, and this aspect is something most people still associate with me. I didn&rsquo;t necessarily feel like I HAD to only paint dinosaurs, but they felt like a reasonable default subject to use to practice different styles. The first painting I did was a somewhat abstract one, where my primary intent was to just practice painting clean lines, but I do like how it turned out.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/dino-1.jpg" type="" alt="Outlines style dino"  /></p>
<p>For my second painting, I wasn&rsquo;t actually intending to paint a dinosaur, I just wanted to try doing shading. This meant individually mixing several different colors and just painting them on progressively from light to dark. On the first day of painting, I just did the background since I wasn&rsquo;t sure what to put on the foreground. One of my friends suggested doing a dinosaur because I &ldquo;always draw dinosaurs everywhere anyways&rdquo;. I couldn&rsquo;t argue with that logic.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/dino-2.jpg" type="" alt="Fiery background dino"  /></p>
<p>Next, I wanted to try doing some proper shading where I just had 1 light color and 1 dark color and mixed them on the paper itself. I looked up videos of people shading cubes, spheres, and cylinders, and realized a dinosaur was basically just a bunch of those put together. I think this one came out very cute!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/dino-3.jpg" type="" alt="3d dino"  /></p>
<p>I discovered Bob Ross shortly before painting this one and wanted to try painting a landscape, including elements like a sunny sky, water, and a tree. I don&rsquo;t think the composition or implementation of this one came out great, but I was still able to squeeze a dinosaur in!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/dino-4.jpg" type="" alt="Landscape dino"  /></p>
<p>After doing a daytime landscape, I felt the natural next step was nighttime. When I was painting the moon, I started with a white circle and started adding on some grey blotches, but realized it was too much, so I quickly blotched off the grey with a paper towel. This created the effect you see on the painting, which I was very pleasantly surprised with!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/dino-5.jpg" type="" alt="Nighttime dino"  /></p>
<p>This is definitely my favorite. I had seen aerial photos of camels and elephants in landscapes where the animal itself is hardly visible, but the shadow is clearer, showing a horizontal view of the animal&rsquo;s silhouette. I decided to make that with dinosaurs! At this point, I had gotten a wide, stiff brush, which was quite fun to use and lead to the broadstrokes texture of the sand. I also tried to make the shadows of the dinosaurs show how the baby dinosaurs were fatigued by the travel.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/dino-6.jpg" type="" alt="Nighttime dino"  /></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
