<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Varun Mangalick</title>
    <link>http://example.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Varun Mangalick</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 20:16:25 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://example.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Painting: the paint wall</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-3-paint-wall/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 20:16:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-3-paint-wall/</guid>
      <description>In January 2022, one of my cousins gave me some extra paints her kids weren&amp;rsquo;t using, which ended up spawning 15+ paint nights over the course of over a year. Things slowed down a bit in 2023, but even so, these paintings formed a giant mosiac paint wall in the living room of my apartment.
Overall, I&amp;rsquo;m up to 57 total paintings (2 not pictured as they&amp;rsquo;re on the second wall) from 20+ people.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Origami design: simple sauropod</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/post-3-dino/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 09:57:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/post-3-dino/</guid>
      <description>My second origami design - the simple sauropod (pics at more angles on the insta):
If you want to fold this, the crease pattern is below.
Here, like with the lizard, I started with a tree diagram and did circle packing through box pleating. In this case, I found I wasn&amp;rsquo;t quite able to pack box pleating squares sufficiently, so I used a technique called the Pythagorean stretch which is what creates the strange polygonal areas in the pattern.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Origami design: baby sea turtle</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/post-2-turtle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Nov 2021 15:46:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/post-2-turtle/</guid>
      <description>My second origami design - the baby sea turtle:
If you want to fold this, the crease pattern is below.
In this case, instead of starting with circle packing, I started by making the pleats I eventually wanted to end up on the back of the shell, then just played around until I felt the head and legs looked about right. For help folding, I made an album with pictures at various stages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Origami design: simple lizard</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/post-1-lizard/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2021 20:30:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/post-1-lizard/</guid>
      <description>My first origami design - the simple lizard:
If you want to fold this, the crease pattern is below.
Most origami design starts with creating a tree structure representing the rough shape of your final figure. Then, you covert terminal nodes in the tree into circles to pack into the square, with each circle corresponding to a spike as long as the circle&amp;rsquo;s radius in the final design. In this case, the final model looks basically the same as the tree diagram, so we can jump right to the circle packing:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Painting: a dinosaur through the eye of Chuck Close</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-2-big-dino/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2018 11:23:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-2-big-dino/</guid>
      <description>At the start of my college junior summer, I painted what is still probably my single favorite thing I&amp;rsquo;ve painted. I was staying with my aunt for a couple days before starting my internship, and I took the opportunity to paint with my artist cousin Sonika didi. She&amp;rsquo;s absolutely fantastic and paints pieces for galleries while also working in art education. See her pieces here!
We looked at a variety of modern artists to get style inspiration, and ended up settling on Chuck Close.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Painting: a series of dinosaurs</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-1-dinos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 21:19:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-1-dinos/</guid>
      <description>During my college freshman summer when I was doing my first internship. I bought paints to have something to do after work, as this was the first time in my life I didn&amp;rsquo;t have homework. This summer, I painted several simple dinosaur paintings!
So why dinosaurs? As a kid, I was obsessed with dinosaurs, and this aspect is something most people still associate with me. I didn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily feel like I HAD to only paint dinosaurs, but they felt like a reasonable default subject to use to practice different styles.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
