<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Varun Mangalick</title>
    <link>http://example.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Varun Mangalick</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 20:16:25 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://example.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Painting: the paint wall</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-3-paint-wall/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 20:16:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-3-paint-wall/</guid>
      <description>In January 2022, one of my cousins gave me some extra paints her kids weren&amp;rsquo;t using, which ended up spawning 15+ paint nights over the course of over a year. Things slowed down a bit in 2023, but even so, these paintings formed a giant mosiac paint wall in the living room of my apartment.
Overall, I&amp;rsquo;m up to 57 total paintings (2 not pictured as they&amp;rsquo;re on the second wall) from 20+ people.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/paint_wall.jpg" type="" alt="A whole wall of paintings"  /></p>
<p>In January 2022, one of my cousins gave me some extra paints her kids weren&rsquo;t using, which ended up spawning 15+ paint nights over the course of over a year. Things slowed down a bit in 2023, but even so, these paintings formed a giant mosiac paint wall in the living room of my apartment.</p>
<p>Overall, I&rsquo;m up to 57 total paintings (2 not pictured as they&rsquo;re on the second wall) from 20+ people. I&rsquo;ve told people they&rsquo;re free to take paintings home, but that they should leave the first one here and come back for it when they paint the second one. This strategy has been successful in having every single painting left here as part of the paint wall.</p>
<p>When people join for paint night, it&rsquo;s pretty unstructured, so everyone can paint what they&rsquo;d like, whether that means following a video, using a picture, or just painting from imagination. As a result, we have a fantastic diversity of subjects and styles! There was only one paint night where multiple people followed the same video, though I did my best to arrange those three paintings far from each other. See if you can spot them!</p>
<p>One of my favorite paintings I&rsquo;ve done is Ocean in a Drop. I started by following a tutorial on painting a water drop, then added a whale along with a school of small red fish. One detail that really helped with the sense of realism was adding slightly offset shadows to the creatures. I posted it <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/painting/comments/uqklix/drop_of_ocean_me_acrylics_on_loose_canvas/">on reddit</a> and got a surprisingly positive reception!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/ocean_drop.jpg" type="" alt="Ocean in a water drop painting"  /></p>
<p>Another favorite is Propaganda Poster of a Plush Dino. I hadn&rsquo;t actually done any dinosaur paintings on this paint wall, so I thought I might as well revisit the old favorite subject. I tried to make the dinosaur fuzzy and 3d to contrast from the bright and flat colors in the background. After painting this, I enjoyed looking back at my 3d dino from <a href="http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-1-dinos/">my freshman summer series</a> and seeing how much I improved on shading since then!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/propaganda_dino.jpg" type="" alt="Propaganda poster of a plush dino painting"  /></p>
<p>COMING SOON: I&rsquo;m going to try to make an interactive version of the paint wall where you can hover over individual paintings and see a blown up image + artist creds. I&rsquo;ll likely publish this as a separate post!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Author commentary (non spoiler)</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/commentary/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2022 18:36:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/commentary/</guid>
      <description>The idea for this story was inspired by a spider mite infestation in my rubber tree. Upon removing the near microscopic mites (with neem spray and a brush), the plant grew more in 1 week than it had in the preceding 6 months.
I was shocked by how much these tiny pests could impact the growth of such a larger organism, and this brought my attention to the numerous other examples in nature including biting flies bothering large mammals (and humans) or various parasitic crustaceans leeching off of whales.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The idea for this story was inspired by a spider mite infestation in my rubber tree. Upon removing the near microscopic mites (with neem spray and a brush), the plant grew more in 1 week than it had in the preceding 6 months.</p>
<p>I was shocked by how much these tiny pests could impact the growth of such a larger organism, and this brought my attention to the numerous other examples in nature including biting flies bothering large mammals (and humans) or various parasitic crustaceans leeching off of whales. Many of these creatures have developed measures to rid themselves of these parasites. For example, scientists believe whales may breach and flipper slap as a way to do so.</p>
<p>This got me thinking of how this sort of system could look on a greatly magnified scale, both in terms of the relevant parasites and potential counter measures by the host animal. This story explores one way this could develop in concert with a specialized form of human society.</p>
<p><a href="http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/chapter-1-the-island/">Read Chapter 1</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Afloat Chapter 6: Departure</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/chapter-6-departure/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 23:15:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/chapter-6-departure/</guid>
      <description>Saltwater assailed Jun’s nose and eyes as he struggled to orient himself. He flailed for a grip onto something, anything, solid to steady himself. As his chest began to grow tight, he felt a grip around his waist, yanking him forward.
Jun broke the surface and breathed in the sweet ocean air. He finally looked around and noticed Alcar holding him and swimming towards the edge of Che’el. Strength slowly returned to Jun’s limbs, but he was far from ready to swim by the time Alcar pushed him onto the island and immediately swam back into the ocean.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Saltwater assailed Jun’s nose and eyes as he struggled to orient himself. He flailed for a grip onto something, anything, solid to steady himself. As his chest began to grow tight, he felt a grip around his waist, yanking him forward.</p>
<p>Jun broke the surface and breathed in the sweet ocean air. He finally looked around and noticed Alcar holding him and swimming towards the edge of Che’el. Strength slowly returned to Jun’s limbs, but he was far from ready to swim by the time Alcar pushed him onto the island and immediately swam back into the ocean. Jun stared into the sky, chest heaving, and felt the static fade from his mind, replaced by growing recollection. The distant island approached, then&hellip;</p>
<p>Then, it dove. What had happened to the people on it? Jun sat up quickly, feeling his head fuzz again, and looked out to the ocean where the island had surfaced. Then he noticed the devastation upon Che’el, which triggered the final memory of a rising crest, towering over him, then rushing down to scour the surface of everyone and everything. Jun looked back and saw swimmers retrieving whomever they could find surfacing amongst the waves.</p>
<p>It was then that Jun saw Jora, a hundred feet away, appearing to float just above the water. He then noticed Elys holding Jora up, her own face dipping underwater more often than not. Jun braced himself, then dove towards them.</p>
<hr>
<p>The inhabitants of Che’el huddled together, cold, hungry, and exhausted. Their island was washed bare by the force of the colossal wave, food, shelter, and freshwater all gone. Some people had cobbled together rafts from the few recovered pieces of wood, but it would be some time before they were able to return with sustenance and assistance.</p>
<p>Jun sat quietly with his family, listening to the snippets of conversation drifting through the crowd. Thankfully he had spotted Elys and Jora and was able to help them back. From what he heard, not every family was so lucky. And while a vast majority of Che’el’s people had made it back, only two of the other island’s people were found alive at all. Too many more must have drowned as they clung to their island, expecting it to support them as it always had.</p>
<p>In the next few hours, rafts approached at an accelerating rate, bearing food, water, and materials for shelter. Upon delivering their payloads, most also took whomever they had space for back to other islands. Eventually, some rafts came bearing historians, including Karu and Rusik, and Jun stood to meet them. He began to narrate in halting words when Karu raised a hand to stop him. “Rest and take care Jun,” she said solemnly. “We are here to help Che’el first, and record history second.”</p>
<p>Jun nodded and trudged back towards his family. As he sat, he looked into the faces of those around him. They looked uneasily at the island which had dove, then at Che’el beneath them. Jun heard Karu sigh and looked up to see her also glancing at the faces of the crowd. “A turtle dives and mankind finally sees the ground beneath their feet as alive.” Karu spoke quietly, and Jun wasn’t sure if anyone had heard but him. Her face grew gaunt, as if she had aged 10 years in a moment. “A turtle dives and mankind finally sees the ground beneath their feet as ground that may not always be theirs to walk upon.”</p>
<hr>
<p>The day after the Dive, Jun and Karu sat down with the survivors of the new island, Katad. “Will you share the story of Katad?” Karu asked. “What could have happened to lead to this?”</p>
<p>Of the two survivors, one had refused to speak in the day since his rescue. The other glanced quickly between Jun and Karu’s faces, then began her tale. “I was not born when we last left the Archipelago. According to our historian, the seamount’s historians warned us that we were departing with too many on our island. The open ocean’s resources would not sustain us as the Archipelago had. We had had many marriages form during our visit, and nearly all of them had chosen to remain on Katad. Those young families were stubborn, and decided to ignore the warning.</p>
<p>“The following years went smoothly, and the new families began to have children, such as myself. The burden upon Katad increased, but we dutifully farmed, gathered, and fished, and we continued to survive. Two decades passed, and many began to wonder when we would next visit the Archipelago and allow our people to settle elsewhere.</p>
<p>“Many more years passed, and my generation began to have children of our own. We were overdue for a visit to the Archipelago, but no one knows the path an island will choose to take. The burden upon Katad increased further, and we starved as we picked off every animal we could find across Katad’s surface.</p>
<p>“One day, one gatherer came to the market with dense chunks of meat. He refused to say what they were, but we were vigilant, and we soon discovered what he had done. Adjacent to a parasite-inflicted wound, he had used a sharpened rock to carve off pieces of Katad’s revealed flesh from beneath the bony outer skin. Within a day, knowledge of this had spread across the island, and the practice quickly gained popularity. Unfortunately, our diligent gathering of parasites had left us few wounds to pick at, but we learned to leave the parasites be so they could create more harvesting sites for ourselves.</p>
<p>“The island’s meat brought us from starvation to excess. Katad, in its limitless capacity, had fed us, and we excitedly planned to share this development the next time we visited the Archipelago. Over the following years, Katad began to swim noticeably faster, but we ignored it until, far in the distance, we finally spotted the Archipelago. It had been more than 40 years since our visit, and we were returning triumphant.”</p>
<p>“The parasite-triggered instinct,” Karu said under her breath, staring aside with unfocused eyes. “It was rushing to obtain humans to cleanse it of its infestation.”</p>
<p>The woman looked at Karu with confusion, then continued. “As we approached, I expected Katad to slow down and enter orbit with the seamount, but instead, Katad began to accelerate. Our historian grew concerned and tried to gain our attention, but we were giddy with excitement. Finally, we could return and flaunt our survival, and the sooner we arrived, the better. Several people climbed down to continue the harvest so we’d have meat to trade upon our arrival. Then&hellip; well, then you saw what happened.”</p>
<p>Karu continued to stare towards nothing. “Perhaps this is another instinct we’ve never had the misfortune to bring forth,” she said. “We live upon these enormous beasts, and for all our records, know so little of them.” She turned to Jun. “Think, even if we keep the actions of Katad’s inhabitants secret, their struggle is bound to be repeated on countless islands as the Erosion progresses.”</p>
<p>Jun thought back to his trip through the seamounts with Lira. Back to the farmers on Pitilo and the stories of a mysterious landmass. Was she right, could people survive on land away from the islands? If there was ever a time to convince people to try, it was now after the Dive shook their confidence in the land they had always called home.. “I have an idea,” Jun said, “but there’s someone I need to introduce you to first.”</p>
<hr>
<p>Jun stood with Lira and Karu on the historians’ meeting ground of Dalom. People from islands all throughout Koatus formed a massive crowd of thousands arrayed before the three of them. The crowd was loosely organized in groups, led by leaders of islands. Jun saw Leta standing before the people of Botar, and even Bors had taken responsibility for the people of Che’el today. Had there ever been so many people on a single island before? Jun looked at Lira and she smiled nervously at him.</p>
<p>“By now, I’m sure you have all heard of the circumstances surrounding Katad,” Karu said. Even the mention of the island drew uneasy looks from those in the crowd. “I’d like to think of this as an isolated instance, but I’m afraid it might not be, given something else we’ve slowly become aware of. We believe the islands are slowly dying out as a species.”</p>
<p>The people of the islands stood silently. Karu seemed to have expected a more immediate reaction, but with their silence, she continued. “We call it the Erosion. Over hundreds of years, the number of islands which come to the Archipelago for the first time seems to be slowly decreasing, and the population of people living on the islands has been slowly increasing. As a result, the islands have grown more and more crowded. Hundreds of years ago, it was common for islands to come and go without being inhabited, but this is rare now. We’ve survived through advances in how we gather, farm, and fish, but this can only carry us so far.”</p>
<p>A low hum arose as murmurs spread through the crowd. The rest of the historians stared intently at Karu. Whether or not they believed in the Erosion, they had all disapproved of sharing knowledge of it outside their circle, and now they waited for what plan or reason Karu would say to justify her choice. “We know this is a lot to process. We’ve only now chosen to share this hypothesis because we have an idea of how to deal with it. Jun, one of our apprentices, will share it.”</p>
<p>The worried crowd and skeptical historians all turned their attention to Jun now. He swallowed nonexistent saliva down his suddenly dry throat. “At Pitilo, the largest of the seamounts, farmers have left their islands to raise trees on the seamount itself. Many of you are probably aware of this, as their cut wood is why we have so many rafts, we don’t have to think twice about using them to row between the islands.</p>
<p>“Pitilo’s tree farmers are still dependent on the islands for food. But maybe they could be self-sufficient if they just cut the amount of wood they need for themselves, and spent more time fishing and gathering coconuts.”</p>
<p>Jun read confusion on the crowd’s faces. “Not that I’m saying they should stop cutting wood for the Archipelago, just that they could maybe survive on their own.” The listeners grew visibly more restless, and Jun tried to shake off his nerves. “What I’m trying to say is, these farmers have shown us that it’s maybe possible to survive on seamounts independent of the islands, especially larger ones like Pitilo which naturally seem to accumulate much more freshwater and large plant species.</p>
<p>“I’ve heard stories of distant masses of land spotted by people on islands out in the ocean, but no one has ever tried to go to one. For good reason, if you took a raft and went, there would be no return. Our islands will swim the course they swim, and so anyone who ventures off would be left behind. I don’t think one person alone could go off and find a way to survive, but what if half of the people of the island went together, ready with tools and extra food? What if half of the people of the island knew from the moment their island left the Archipelago that they’d be perpetually watchful for such a landmass and constantly preparing to leave for it once one was spotted?</p>
<p>“If some islands decide to take on this responsibility, and they actually find a land mass, then the remaining members of the island will eventually return to the Archipelago to inform the rest of us. If we’re lucky and the island stays by the landmass for long enough, maybe the settlers can even send a messenger back to tell us how it turned out to be. If these landmasses really are so much bigger than even Pitilo, imagine what life we’ll discover on them!”</p>
<p>Jun glanced at Lira and saw her grin, hearing him use her arguments. If she hadn’t joined his trip, he never would have come up with this plan. Looking back to the crowd, Jun saw the murmurs continue, though more faces showed optimism than they had in moments prior. Then Karu stepped forward to speak. “We will need volunteers for the first expedition. If there is enough interest, we could even set up more than one island to take settlers, though I would also think it reasonable to wait until the first island returns with news of success or failure. I will join the first party, who will join me?”</p>
<p>The murmurs died down, and the air was filled with an expectant silence. Jun had hoped more people would have been swayed by his plan, especially in the aftermath of the Dive, but maybe the other historians were right. Maybe the Erosion was too much for people to accept. Suddenly, Jun found himself stepping forward, as if his legs acted of their own accord. “I too will join the first party. Will no one else have the courage to join us?”</p>
<p>Jun’s heart raced. He could never leave Che’el! But at the same time, some part of him knew that his plan’s success was more important. If this didn’t happen now, he’d drift off on Che’el, leaving a broken plan behind. It might take years or even decades for someone to come up with a better idea, and even then, who knows if people could be convinced to follow it? Jun looked at Lira, the obvious question in his eyes, but she just shook her head subtly.</p>
<p>“We shall join you!”</p>
<p>Jun turned towards the source of the voice. A young couple, not yet with children, stood up and walked over to Jun, Lira, and Karu. And then, another family, with three kids just older than Jun, joined as well. Group after group shuffled over until several dozen stood ready. Karu met Jun’s gaze and gave him a small nod. “Thank you,” she said, addressing the volunteers. “I will share more details regarding our preparation, and for the rest of you,” she said, now addressing the crowd, “thank you for your time. I hope you find a way to bring the islands back, but if not, I hope you find the courage to join us eventually.”</p>
<p>As Karu talked more to the volunteers, Jun pulled Lira aside. “Why don’t you come with us? You know how important this is, and I wouldn’t have even come up with this plan without you.”</p>
<p>“I know, but can you really see yourself leaving Che’el and your family? If you do this, you probably won’t ever see them again.</p>
<p>Jun glanced at the crowd, but there were too many present to pick out his mother or father. “I know I won&rsquo;t, but this feels important. This is about the survival of all of us, and if I just abandon it, I don’t know if I’ll ever do anything as important ever again.”</p>
<p>“I know,” she said, “but we don’t know how long it’s going to take to convince people to follow. What happens to those left behind? Those living on the island as they get more and more crowded. Even if everyone agrees to seek out landmasses, it might take years before even one island finds one, forget about the rest. We’ve got to keep learning to survive more efficiently with what we’ve got, and I just think I’ve got to stay to help figure that out, for my family and for everyone.”</p>
<p>Jun measured Lira’s expression and realized that, as set as he was upon going, she was upon staying. As enthusiastic as he would be about exploring new land, she would be about finding ways to help make sure everyone survived to reach it.</p>
<hr>
<p>Jun finished packing his things and stood up to face his family. “I’m sorry,” he mumbled, “I wish I didn’t have to&hellip;”</p>
<p>“I understand,” Alcar said, putting a hand on Jun’s shoulder. “You’ve set your mind to it, and I know there’s no getting around that. Besides, I’d be pretty tempted to do the same if I were your age.”</p>
<p>Elys stood closer to Jun and put an arm around his shoulders. “Besides, we’ll be on the first island out soon as Jora is old enough to be a little more independent. Maybe we’ll even end up in the same place.”</p>
<p>Jun stood with them, silently for several minutes that seemed to stretch on for an eternity. Once he pulled away, however, it felt like it had been no time at all. He took a raft to join Karu and the rest of the volunteers as they gathered on Parek, the island they would depart on. Karu and the other historian volunteers believed it would be the next to leave the Archipelago, so they brought their clothes, their shelters, and their tools, and set up a new home.</p>
<p>The first night Jun slept on Parek, something felt off. He had spent a vast majority of his nights in the Archipelago sleeping on islands that were not Che’el, but each of those times still felt like a visit away from home. The slight difference in rhythm or timbre of the deep and distant heartbeats were always temporary. Parek, however, would be his home for the foreseeable future, with Che’el’s rhythm now just a memory of his past. And one day, he’d leave behind the islands with their deep rhythms all together.</p>
<p>The next day, they continued to build up shelters and lay down farming soil. By night, Jun&rsquo;s body ached from the labor and his eyelids sagged as he settled in for the night. This time, Parek&rsquo;s heartbeat didn&rsquo;t feel quite as foreign, though maybe it was just the exhaustion.</p>
<p>As the first light rose over the water, Jun rubbed the sleep from his eyes, and as he looked around, his breath caught in his throat. The Archipelago was gone. He saw Karu sitting and staring out to the ocean behind them. &ldquo;I guess there&rsquo;s no turning back now,&rdquo; Jun said.</p>
<p>&ldquo;No, I guess not.&rdquo;</p>
<hr>
<p><a href="http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/commentary/">Read author commentary</a></p>
<p><a href="http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/">Back to story home page</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Afloat Chapter 5: The Dive</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/chapter-5-the-dive/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 23:27:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/chapter-5-the-dive/</guid>
      <description>Jun stuffed his things into a knapsack, clothes and food for two full days. Coming back to Che’el, he had hoped to see his family, but he finally came home during a time when they were out. Lira, however, trailed behind him, peppering him with questions. “What’s going on? Where are you headed in such a rush?”
“It’s all real, Lira,” Jun responded. “The Erosion is real, and we have to find a way to stop it!</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jun stuffed his things into a knapsack, clothes and food for two full days. Coming back to Che’el, he had hoped to see his family, but he finally came home during a time when they were out. Lira, however, trailed behind him, peppering him with questions. “What’s going on? Where are you headed in such a rush?”</p>
<p>“It’s all real, Lira,” Jun responded. “The Erosion is real, and we have to find a way to stop it!”</p>
<p>“The Erosion? What are you talking about?”</p>
<p>Jun recounted his conversation with Karu, and he watched Lira’s expression sink. As he started stating the conclusions Karu had come to, Lira raised an eyebrow. “So the historians are working on this, and it won’t be a big issue until long after we’re dead,” Lira said, talking over him. “So what are you expecting to do right now?”</p>
<p>“Don’t you understand? Che’el won’t stay here forever, so if we want to do something about this, we have to do it now.”</p>
<p>“I guess,” Lira said hesitantly, “but as I said, what are you expecting to do right now?”</p>
<p>“Every seamount must have historians who are thinking about what caused this or how to fix it, but they’re too afraid to openly discuss it. I’m sure they’ve figured out pieces of this puzzle, and if I can talk to them and figure out what those are, maybe we can put them together to find a solution!”</p>
<p>“But the historians won&rsquo;t accept anyone who talks about it openly,” Lira said. “Jun, don’t you want to be a historian?”</p>
<p>Jun looked out in the distance in the direction of Dalom, then back down to Che’el’s shell beneath his feet. “I never really thought I was going to leave Che’el and stay in the Archipelago. I couldn’t leave everyone behind. And now that I’ve seen how the historians have covered up the Erosion, I’m even less sure I want to join them, even if I want to do what they do.”</p>
<p>Lira nodded subtly in agreement. “When are you planning on leaving for the next seamount?”</p>
<p>“Tomorrow at first light,” Jun said. “We’ll need to go quickly to make it by night, and even so, I’ll sleep tonight on one of the islands on the edge of our cluster.”</p>
<p>“I’ll be ready.”</p>
<hr>
<p>Jun and Lira stood at the front and back of their raft, paddling in sync to propel themselves smoothly forward. In the months they had spent on the Archipelago, they had considerably improved their ability on the raft, given it was the primary form of transport between islands. Even so, journeying to the next seamount, Pitilo, would occupy the vast majority of the day.</p>
<p>As during Bors’s first arrival to Koatus, Jun and Lira threaded their way through the other islands until they arrived to those most adjacent to the seamount itself. Pitilo was noticeably broader than Koatus, though of a similar height and with a more rounded peak. The surface appeared softer and more brown and green in contrast to Koatus’s rocky black and gray. The waters seemed even more full of coral reefs and schools of fish, something Jun had hardly thought possible. As they pulled up their raft to an island, they came close enough to the seamount for Jun to notice structures on its slopes.</p>
<p>They were soon approached by the leader of this island. They made their introductions, and in conversation, learned more about the seamount. Pitilo was the largest of the seamounts, and as a result, tended to have the most islands in its orbit. While research on the islands of Pitilo had historically been in a similar vein to that which happened on the islands of Koatus, recently, some farmers had discovered trees growing on the seamount much taller and straighter than anything they had grown on the islands. In addition, these large trees grew coconuts which, when opened, contained sweet water and flesh. While these farmers still depended on the islands for much of their food, they seemed to be prospering, and their numbers were growing.</p>
<p>Jun joined a historians’ meeting on an island of Pitilo and listened impatiently as they discussed updates on arriving and departing islands, similar to what the historians of Koatus had discussed. As the meeting concluded, Jun joined a conversation with several historians and gently probed for knowledge about the Erosion. Most seem confused, but a minority glared then pointedly turned away. One took his arm and pulled him aside. “Who is your mentor? They should have put that notion out of your head before you brought it up here.”</p>
<p>Jun pulled his arm free. “I come from Koatus and don’t have one of your mentors. What is wrong with my idea?”</p>
<p>The historian searched Jun’s expression for evidence of sincerity. “I thought Koatus had disallowed this nonsense, but perhaps things have changed there. If you’d like to stay on an island of Pitilo, think more carefully on your words. We don’t allow our historians to spread dangerous delusions.”</p>
<p>Jun angrily stalked away. He wandered from island to island, absentmindedly searching for Lira as he waited for evening when they planned to meet back at their original landing point. At some point, he realized he was searching in the wrong place. Jun rowed to the seamount itself and found Lira amongst the seamount farmers. As she saw him approach, she pulled away from her conversation to join him. “Jun, I can’t believe what they’re able to do here.”</p>
<p>Seeing her enthusiasm, Jun was happy to put his frustrations aside. “Really, why don’t you tell me?”</p>
<p>Lira led Jun excitedly through the farmers’ impromptu village, where scattered palm trees surrounded grassy shelters. Between them, farmers congregated and sipped from large green coconuts. Lira explained how their harvesting of the palm and other tree trunks on the seamount fueled the recent ubiquity of rafts across the entire Archipelago. Even just a couple years ago, travel between islands was much more limited.</p>
<p>More recently, the demand for the seamount’s trees slowed, and so the farmers began to explore what else this new land, as large as 20 islands, could provide them. As they climbed up the seamount, they found many natural freshwater ponds, each as large as those laboriously carved into the surface of the islands. Upon reaching the peak, they discovered a magnificent turquoise lake nestled in a massive depression. The farmers informed them that during heavy rainfall, the lake would overflow the bounds of its crater and send tributaries down to slopes to fill the many ponds and eventually join the ocean.</p>
<p>The farmers hadn’t planned to stay long on the seamount, but with every passing day of bountiful harvest, they grew more settled in. Supported by trade with the islands, they had a comfortable life. However, even Pitilo was only large enough to support a fraction of the people who lived on the islands which floated around it. Perhaps even fewer than its size would suggest, since this land which so easily put forth plant life was void of the parasitic organisms Jun had learned to survive off of.</p>
<p>Jun and Lira slept on the seamount, and come morning, departed. After the reception Jun received from Pitilo’s historians, he knew there was little more for him to learn here. Over the course of weeks. they journeyed between half a dozen more seamounts in the Archipelago. Jun would acquaint himself with the local historians while Lira would search for trades or techniques not found elsewhere. None of the seamounts seemed to permit open discussion of the Erosion, but the generality of knowledge of it varied strongly between them.</p>
<p>In one small seamount, island residents began to build out large rafts, fueled by harvesting in Pitilo, which they connected to their seamount to expand its area. This space was primarily used for trades such as fish leather tanning as few besides the tanners would willingly choose to live near the resulting stench. Jun asked about the inception of this idea and eventually traced it back to Erosion-accepting historians. While they were loath to admit it, Jun guessed they pushed for this in case the extra space would be needed to support people as the islands dwindled.</p>
<p>Lira hadn’t found as many novel practices as she had hoped; Koatus and Pitilo seemed to excel in that regard. Eventually, she started asking people of various islands about the things they had seen on their islands’ travels. Some tales she dismissed as fanciful, such as those of great serpents silently swimming round the island, never breaching the surface, or ghostly glowing swirls in the water which shone with every ripple, but only in the darkest of nights.</p>
<p>Other tales seemed more intriguing. One fisherman found husks which resembled Pitilo’s coconuts, but he claimed to have done so long before Pitilo began farming, and during a time when his island was far from the Archipelago. A gatherer spoke of what appeared to be a great seamount far away by the horizon. A mass of land as tall as Pitilo, but stretching wide in both directions, wide enough for the land to dwarf the Archipelago altogether. However, the gatherer’s island continued upon the path it chose, and he never saw that mass upon the water again.</p>
<p>Jun and Lira rowed gently through the calm ocean water, finally headed back towards Che’el. Weeks of hectic travel had left them quiet and reflective for the journey back. “Do you think people could live on that landmass?” Lira said quietly.</p>
<p>Jun looked to Lira, seeing the careful consideration in her expression. Over the course of their travels, she’d taken more to thinking about the Erosion than he’d expected. Maybe she wasn’t so stubborn after all. “Even the farmers on Pitilo rely on trade for gathered meat. They could hardly survive on only coconuts.”</p>
<p>“Sure, but that’s because coconuts are all they have on Pitilo. But just think about how much better coconuts are than any trees or plants we can grow on Koatus or our islands. The farmers believed Pitilo could grow them because it was large enough to accumulate fresh water and dirt. If that’s the case, imagine what sort of trees could grow on a landmass 10 or 20 times as big as Pitilo!” Lira’s eyes were bright with excitement. “Maybe they’d be enough for us to survive without needing to rely on the islands.”</p>
<p>“Even if you’re right, how would we even find that landmass again? It’s just a story from years ago.” Jun couldn’t imagine a life lived there. The night he had slept on Pitilo, he pressed his ear to the earth like he did each night, but for the first time he could remember, the only response was silence. Che’el had fed him, housed him, and carried him through the ocean to always fresh and fertile waters. On Pitilo, or even this mysterious landmass, Jun felt he’d have to wrench his sustenance from the dead rocks beneath his feet.</p>
<hr>
<p>Many days later, Jun and Lira arrived at Che’el, and they docked their raft. Lira gave Jun a sheepish smile, then went off to find her family. Their journey hadn’t answered as many questions as Jun had hoped, but he still wanted to find Karu to talk about the possibility of encouraging the settlement of Koatus, like what had been done at Pitilo. Maybe they could look through the records for more sightings of the landmass to get a better sense of its location.</p>
<p>Jun greeted Elys as he approached their family shelter. Alcar was still working intently on disassembling and preserving his day’s catch, but Elys, holding Jora, sat Jun down to talk about his journey. He started to describe the trees of Pitilo when he noticed Elys’s eyes wander towards something in the distance behind him. Jun turned around and saw what appeared to be an island approaching Che’el from a couple of miles away.</p>
<p>The island’s front flippers rose into the air and struck down into the water at a pace which appeared glacial at a distance, but was still faster than Jun had ever seen done by Che’el. More and more of Che’el’s inhabitants emerged to watch the new island joining Koatus.</p>
<p>Over several minutes, the new island continued to draw closer, showing no sign of slowing. Islands had certainly come closer to Che’el as they floated around the Archipelago, but none with this speed. “Is it going to hit us?” Jun asked Alcar.</p>
<p>“It’s never happened before, it won’t happen today,” Alcar said. However, his brows were knitted with worry. They watched the island approach, growing larger and larger in their vision. When the island was less than a mile away, Jun noticed angry red patches on the island’s skin near the base of its neck and flippers. They looked almost like the patches left behind by parasites, but far larger as to be visible from this distance.</p>
<p>Closer and closer the island crept, and Jun’s view grew ever clearer. Small dark spots appeared adjacent to the red patches, looking almost like biting flies buzzing at a wound. Several minutes later, Jun picked out arms and legs and realized the spots were people. Several more minutes passed by, and Jun started to see the motion of their arms striking down onto the island’s skin. Were they dislodging parasites? How had the damage grown so much?</p>
<p>The island was now less than half a mile away, and Jun couldn’t seem to figure out what the people upon it were doing. The island stared forward, expression inscrutable as it continued its advance. The people of Che’el, initially standing at the edge facing the oncoming island, now started to back away. “Gather your things,” Alcar shouted, “and head for the rafts!”</p>
<p>The crowd ran across the island, a select few stopping to gather tools or food. Jun continued to glance back as he ran. The island grew larger and larger in his vision, and suddenly he realized what its inhabitants had done. With each strike to the island’s skin, they tore off meat to consume. All people owed their survival to their islands, but on this island, people decided to remove the middle link of the food chain. On this island, humans had become the lampreys, the copepods, the amphipods, and they fed on the island far more ferociously than the creatures they replaced.</p>
<p>Jun looked into the approaching island’s eyes once more. Was that determination or pain that drove it forward? Then, over the course of a minute, the island plunged its flippers into the ocean far deeper than it had on the other strokes. It pulled the flippers back and up, and slowly but surely, the island began to dip beneath the surface. Jun grabbed his father’s arm, and his family stopped and watched in horror as the people of the island dashed about, most eventually clinging to the shell’s surface. The island sank, bit by bit, until every trace of it and the people upon it had disappeared beneath the waves.</p>
<p>Elys gestured to the crowd to get their attention. “We have to save them, follow me to this side of the island! We can take rafts out!”</p>
<p>Alcar took her hand between his. “I’ll go to help them, but you take Jun and Jora on a raft on the other side of the island and get as far away as you can.”</p>
<p>Elys pulled him back towards where the island had sunk. “You saw how many people were on that island, we’ll all be needed to rescue them. Don’t forget that I can swim as well as you can.”</p>
<p>Alcar looked back to the now calm waters. “It’s not your swimming I’m worried about. That island has to come up sometime or another.”</p>
<p>Jun watched Elys look pleadingly at Alcar. Across the crowd, similar conversations appeared to take place as people slowly split off either to help the rescue effort or to join the evacuation. Jun looked back to the sea. If the islands were naturally buoyant as Rusik had told him, then his dad was right, it would surface eventually. He continued to watch as the group finally split and Alcar gestured for him to join the rescue swimmers and paddlers. He turned to see Elys carry Jora away with the rest, then ran to catch up with Alcar.</p>
<p>They approached the edge and began to distribute rafts when someone shouted, pointing out at the water. Jun looked up and saw a subtle swell form on the ocean’s surface. Then, the island’s head broke the surface, its body accelerating upwards to follow it. The island rose higher out of the water than Jun would have imagined possible, streams of white agitated water rushing from every crevice back into the ocean. Right as the island hit the peak of its rise, it accelerated downwards, the whole motion reminding Jun of a bobbing piece of wood surfacing after being held underwater.</p>
<p>The island’s sudden rise and crash churned the ocean to a froth. As Jun watched, a swell rushed away from the surfaced island in all directions. As it approached Che’el, it grew. Jun’s feet felt cemented to the surface, though the men and women around him had begun to flee. The wave grew, now tall enough to cover the sky, and in the last moment before it hit, Alcar took Jun’s arm and held him close.</p>
<p><a href="http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/chapter-6-departure/">Read Chapter 6</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Afloat Chapter 4: The Erosion</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/chapter-4-the-erosion/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 14:49:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/chapter-4-the-erosion/</guid>
      <description>As he read and wrote endless records of island arrivals and departures, Jun kept track of the patterns he noticed. While islands tended to spend a majority of their time away from the Archipelago, both their visits and the times between tended to increase in duration as the islands grew older. Hundreds of years ago, historians discovered that the oldest islands in the Archipelago showed their age through fogged eyes and brittle shells which flaked off keratin constantly.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As he read and wrote endless records of island arrivals and departures, Jun kept track of the patterns he noticed. While islands tended to spend a majority of their time away from the Archipelago, both their visits and the times between tended to increase in duration as the islands grew older. Hundreds of years ago, historians discovered that the oldest islands in the Archipelago showed their age through fogged eyes and brittle shells which flaked off keratin constantly. When these islands left, they did so permanently, likely searching out a place to die in solitude. Despite this knowledge, the inhabitants of the aging island Tulora refused to migrate to a younger island when Tulora was preparing to leave. They departed, never to be seen again.</p>
<p>Jun treasured his conversations with Rusik just as much if not more than before. He spent much of the time discussing his discoveries to see which were unknown, proven wrong, or common knowledge, though none ended up being in the first category.</p>
<p>Some records illustrated how much even his life on Che’el had benefited from the scientific advances of the Archipelago. The tanning of fish leather using black kelp had just been discovered 50 years ago, and the edible and structural plants grown on Che’el were already the result of generations of work spent on selective breeding. Upon hearing of this, Lira grew even more excited about her pursuit of new practical knowledge so she could continue the long tradition of Che’el’s improvement.</p>
<p>In a record from centuries past, Jun read of islands which arrived and departed unsettled by people. New families only moved to the frontier of new land when their original islands grew too crowded, but even then, they often stayed on the Archipelago, hopping islands until they had established a trade well enough to join a newly settled departing island. After reading this, Jun peered out across the hundreds of islands of Koatus in confusion. While exploring, he had seen one or two unsettled islands which seemed small enough for this to be their first visit, though unsettled islands were much more rare a sight than the record would have led him to believe.</p>
<p>With Rusik’s permission, Jun borrowed and scanned through summary records of decades spread across the past millennium. He had a dozen guesses racing through his head, but evidence eliminated them one by one. The islands didn’t seem to be staying for less time or leaving for longer. Islands didn’t seem to be dying at a higher rate. The estimated total number of people did seem to be increasing, but not fast enough to account for the increase in crowding in the Archipelago.</p>
<p>Finally, Jun found a promising thread to pull and possibly unravel this knot. The number of unsettled islands which arrived at the Archipelago seemed to decrease each century. Jun initially attributed this to the fact that some of the arriving islands were repeat arrivals; they weren’t properly named or tracked until they were settled. An increasing population would mean fewer unsettled islands leaving and therefore fewer unsettled islands arriving, but what if there were actually fewer islands being born and arriving for the first time?</p>
<p>While the arriving islands hadn’t been named, thankfully they had been measured, and these measurements had been preserved at least for the last couple of centuries. Jun counted up the number of arriving islands which were small enough to perhaps be first arrivals, and while the trend was slight, it was undeniable: the number of islands being born appeared to be decreasing.</p>
<p>As Jun finished sharing his findings, Lira furrowed her brow, puzzled. “So fewer islands are coming to the Archipelago?” she asked. “Where are they going then?”</p>
<p>“That’s what I’m trying to tell you,” Jun said, “they’re not going anywhere else. There are just fewer islands being born and making it to the Archipelago for the first time.”</p>
<p>Lira remained visibly puzzled. “But if that were the case, wouldn’t we have noticed? How would there still be enough islands for us to live on? For us to have always lived on?”</p>
<p>“I don’t know if it’s always been decreasing or if it started several hundred years ago, but it’s happening so slowly, no one would really be able to tell a difference in a lifetime.”</p>
<p>“So, let’s say the islands end up becoming a little more crowded,” Lira said. “That’s the whole point of everything I’ve been learning! Over time, we learn how to gather, fish, and plant more efficiently than we could before. We’ll keep learning and keep improving.”</p>
<p>“But what if one day, the islands are all gone? What can we learn to make up for that?”</p>
<p>“We’d find a way.”</p>
<p>Frustrated, Jun headed towards Che’el. Lira didn’t understand, but she had always been the type to be too occupied by what she was doing at that moment. Unless he could convince her to apprentice with the historians, she’d obsess over plants and birds until the sun went down. He walked to his family’s shelter to talk to Alcar. Alcar had taught him everything he knew about observation, he would listen.</p>
<p>The conversation started out fairly similar to the one Jun had had with Lira. But as Jun explained his process of deduction again, Alcar started to nod with some understanding if not acceptance. “Clearly you took my advice,” Alcar said. “But are you sure about this? Have you mentioned this to the historians?”</p>
<p>“I want to, but I need to talk to someone first and make sure I’m not crazy.” Jun threw his hands up with frustration. “They haven’t even let me join discussions, and I want to start off by telling them that the world is going to end?”</p>
<p>Alcar stared off into the distance, deep in thought. “I know it seems like a lot, but if you did your due diligence, there’s no reason to feel embarrassed to talk about where your reasoning brought you.”</p>
<p>“And what if I’m wrong?”</p>
<p>Alcar continued, still seeming to have only half a mind focused on his words. “If you’re wrong, I’d be far happier than if you’re right. But if you are right&hellip;” He trailed off, taking a moment to form his words. “Not everyone will want to hear this. We’ve always lived on the islands, and if we couldn’t, I’m not sure what we’d do.”</p>
<hr>
<p>Jun walked with Rusik towards a meeting of the historians. Sometime after his conversation with Alcar, Jun found out from Rusik that he would finally be allowed to join the meetings. As they walked, Jun played out a dozen versions of the words in his head. How was he supposed to bring up his hypothesis? Perhaps it would be easier to broach the topic with just Rusik first.</p>
<p>“Rusik, there’s something I want to discuss at the meeting, but can I run it by you first?” Jun asked.</p>
<p>Rusik smiled at him. “Couple of months ago, you wouldn’t have even asked. Of course, what is it?”</p>
<p>Jun once again walked through his reasoning including all of his enumerated possibilities and how he had eliminated all of them but one. As Rusik listened, his eyes grew grave, more so than Jun had ever seen since meeting him. After Jun finished, Rusik shook his head, as if to dissuade a bothering gnat, and then suddenly his expression lightened back up. “That’s an interesting idea, but ideas of that sort have been disproven dozens of times.”</p>
<p>Expecting to hear a more surprised and disbelieving response, Jun had started to line up further evidence and figures to support his idea, but Rusik’s seemingly offhand dismissal left him taken aback. “Are you sure?” he asked hesitantly. “Can you show me how this is disproven? I can show you more of my work?”</p>
<p>Rusik turned to face the other historians as he and Jun approached the group which had begun to congregate. Rusik seemed to be focused on greeting the other historians, so Jun resolved to continue the discussion after the meeting. The topics discussed were mostly mundane, including detailed recounting of events from some newly arrived islands as well as updates on the movement of populations throughout the Archipelago. Jun found his mind treading the steps of his investigation over and over, trying to figure out what mistake he could have made. But each iteration only seemed to strengthen his conviction in his belief.</p>
<p>After the meeting, Jun tried to talk to Rusik, but the man was swept up in conversations with partners who meandered away surprisingly quickly. Jun needed to talk to someone, and so he worked up the courage to approach Karu. “There’s something I want to ask you about. I was reading the records and came up with a pretty scary theory about the islands, and I just want to talk it through with someone to see if I’m just being silly.”</p>
<p>Karu looked down with annoyance as if to shoo him away, but seeing Jun’s evident agitation, she relaxed her frown. “Tell me quickly, what is it?”</p>
<p>Jun once again talked through his findings, and as he finished, he waited for the inevitable dismissal, likely accompanied by harsher words than Rusik’s. To his surprise, Karu ushered him away from the gathering. “I didn’t expect you to notice, especially so soon.”</p>
<p>Jun was once again taken aback. Karu saw his expression and continued. “We call it the Erosion. Those of us that accept it of course. I don’t know how long ago the first historian noticed it, but for years, those who knew of the Erosion would not speak of it, as if giving it voice would cause it to occur. Eventually, enough historians independently reached the same conclusion, and they discovered each other.</p>
<p>“In secret, they collected evidence, checked each others’ work, and polished their arguments until they shone with inarguable truth. Emboldened by solidarity, they presented their findings to the other historians in gatherings across the Archipelago. Most of the listeners dove into the records to perform their own calculations, but over time, they all split into two groups. Some finally accepted the Erosion, but far, far more denied it.</p>
<p>“The deniers of the Erosion, with their vast majority, conferred and came to a stance: Even if the Erosion is true, if we have no way to address it, then we cannot let it be known. They told us believers that we were forbidden from speaking of this to any who did not already know. They hoped to avoid a panic among the populace, but even among the historians, they wanted to maintain a focus on understanding island biology and how to maximize life upon them.</p>
<p>“I’ll never know how many of the deniers truly did not believe in the Erosion versus how many simply refused to accept what they could not fix. But from then on, our numbers have grown only from historians like you who have discovered the truth and talked to the right person.”</p>
<p>Jun stared at Karu, his brain struggling to process what he was hearing. He was right! “So what does that mean for me? Do I get to join extra secret meetings now?”</p>
<p>Karu sighed. “You’re about 20 years too late. We used to meet more, but we’ve come to the conclusions we will come to, and we’ve mostly given up.”</p>
<p>Jun imagined Karu and the other believers of the Erosion, clearly the most observant of the historians, passionately discussing causes and solutions for the Erosion. But he couldn’t imagine them giving up. “What conclusions did you come to?”</p>
<p>“The Erosion is occurring slowly enough that in conjunction with general scientific advancement on the Archipelago, we should have a hundred years or more before we begin running into issues, but once we reach that point, it would be difficult to find a solution.”</p>
<p>“Why?”</p>
<p>“The more crowded we get, the harder it will be to feed everyone on the resources of the islands and the Archipelago. Without excess food, we shall lose our excess time, and without that, research and our study of history shall grind to a half. The second conclusion was that the seamounts could house small populations to temporarily alleviate-”</p>
<p>“Living on the seamounts?” Jun asked incredulously. “I know the Archipelago has lots of fish, but how would people survive on just plants and fish without gathered meat?”</p>
<p>Karu sniffed with annoyance. “As I was saying, it could temporarily alleviate crowding, but we’re not sure if living on the seamounts would encourage fishing at a level which could drain the populations around the Archipelago. We believe planting may be more viable there due to freshwater streams which seem to originate from higher up on the peak, but we haven’t found a believable excuse to send people to try.”</p>
<p>Jun thought for a moment. “What if you figured out the cause of the Erosion and fixed that?”</p>
<p>“Believe me, we’ve tried,” Karu said. “As far as we can tell, the islands feed at a massive scale on whatever ocean life they encounter. Their waste then fertilizes the growth of life in their wake. As long as there is life, there are islands. But as we’ve examined records of fishing success for islands which have returned to the Archipelago across the last few centuries, we’ve found a slight decline in their catches which parallels the decline in the population of the islands.”</p>
<p>“Decline of fish? You don’t think&hellip;” Jun said, trailing off in thought. “Could it be from us? Are we eating too many of the fish?”</p>
<p>“I doubt it,” Karu replied. “Like the islands, we return our waste to the ocean, and like the islands, we fertilize new life to compensate for what we take. This is different. It is as if God has reached down to reclaim his gift of creation for himself.”</p>
<p><a href="http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/chapter-5-the-dive/">Read Chapter 5</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Afloat Chapter 3: The Archipelago</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/chapter-3-the-archipelago/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 23:15:42 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/chapter-3-the-archipelago/</guid>
      <description>The Archipelago had existed since long before the humans upon it began keeping written records. It was centered around a chain of underwater mountains, or seamounts, formed from the fiery eruptions of a pool of magma which seemed to drift along the ocean’s floor over the millenia. Only the tallest seamounts breached the ocean’s surface, but every mount, short or tall, shaped the currents to create a fertile bed of life.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Archipelago had existed since long before the humans upon it began keeping written records. It was centered around a chain of underwater mountains, or seamounts, formed from the fiery eruptions of a pool of magma which seemed to drift along the ocean’s floor over the millenia. Only the tallest seamounts breached the ocean’s surface, but every mount, short or tall, shaped the currents to create a fertile bed of life.</p>
<p>For many of the island turtles, these waters were ideal grounds for resting or mating. Once a turtle had arrived, it might stay for years, and so the Archipelago tended to host thousands of turtles at any given time. And with them, came the hundreds of thousands of humans that lived upon their shells.</p>
<hr>
<p>Jun’s eyes shot open to the sounds of Alcar and Elys packing knapsacks with food and other supplies. Outside his shelter, he could hear a hum of activity as the whole island seemed to be doing the same. “Have we arrived?”</p>
<p>Alcar gestured outside. “Take a look for yourself.”</p>
<p>Jun peeked his head out. What had once been open ocean was now peppered with islands in every direction. While Che’el was not the smallest of the islands Jun saw, it was definitely smaller than most. At the center of the group was a seamount, reaching into the sky, with a rocky surface mottled black, gray, and green. Sea birds flocked around nests dotting the portions of the rock nearest to the water’s edge.</p>
<p>Jun turned back to Alcar. “Why didn’t you wake me up earlier?” he asked.</p>
<p>“You have an exciting day ahead of you, and I thought you could use the rest,” Alcar said. “Besides, what would you have done? I’ve got everything just about ready to go.”</p>
<p>Jun sighed and ran out to find Lira. In truth, it was probably best that he had slept longer; even now he unsuccessfully stifled a yawn which left his jaw cracked and aching. He had aimed to be up with the first light to watch the final arrival into the Archipelago, and as a result, his sleep was fitful, plagued with dreams of waking up to find Che’el already having departed with the Archipelago long behind them.</p>
<p>The last time Che’el had visited the Archipelago was when Jun’s parents had met. Che’el had stayed for 4 years during that visit, which was just enough time for Elys to meet Alcar, fall in love, and convince him to move to Che’el with her. Visits to the Archipelago were often accompanied by a flurry of romance and shuffling of communities. It was uncommon, if not rare, for couples to form within an island during Archipelago visits, but as time wore on after, people relented and formed families with those around them.</p>
<p>As the first raft was placed in the water, Jun and Lira pressed forward through the crowd waiting to embark upon it. Lira’s father Bors was preparing to board with a collection of records when Lira approached him. “Please can we go first?”</p>
<p>Bors spoke to the historian accompanying him. “Let them go. We will have years to handle our affairs, but they’ve been waiting their whole lives for this moment.”</p>
<p>The historian nodded and gestured for Jun and Lira to step onto the raft. Once they sat, Bors began to row with an oar of knobby wood and woven grass. Slowly, they drifted along the water, threading between various islands and working their way towards the seamount. While the narrowest gaps between islands still measured hundreds of steps, Bors tended to pass close enough to several islands for Jun to see the faces of the people living and working upon them. They were the first people he had ever seen who didn’t live on Che’el.</p>
<p>An hour or so passed, and Jun found himself wondering how Bors had determined their destination. As he was about to ask, Bors ceased rowing and steered the raft to a gentle stop at one of the islands directly adjacent to the seamount. Jun and Lira hopped onto the island as a woman emerged from a shelter to meet them. Bors stayed on the raft, but looked up to address the woman. “My name is Bors, and we live on the island Che’el. This is Lira and Jun,” he said, pointing to them, “two of our children born since our last visit.”</p>
<p>The woman gave Bors a long slow nod before responding. “Welcome to the Archipelago. I am Leta, and I live on the island Botar. We swim in the shadow of Koatus.”</p>
<p>Bors looked over Leta’s shoulder at the black spire behind her. From this distance, Koatus rose even more intimidatingly upwards, high enough to block the sun at midmorning. Its mottled surface was now revealed to be a patchwork of birds’ nests, plants, and lichens. “Thank you Leta,” Bors said. “I shall bring our historian next, along with more of our people, but until then, may I leave the children? They wish to learn more about the Archipelago, but my memories will need to be refreshed.”</p>
<p>Leta walked up to Jun and Lira and placed a hand on Lira’s shoulder. “We look forward to meeting your people, but until then, Jun and Lira will be safe in my care. I am the leader of Botar, and we have been long enough with Koatus to be quite familiar.”</p>
<p>With that, Bors gave his farewell and began his journey back. Jun peered in the direction Bors headed and tried to pick out Che’el from the several islands, but felt disconcerted that he couldn’t do so. Lira noticed his frown and looked at him with confusion, but he just shook his head and smiled back. Leta began to walk back towards the island’s center, and Jun and Lira followed behind. “So what would you two like to know?” Leta asked.</p>
<p>Lira and Jun looked to each other, both struggling to contain growing grins. Jun turned back to address Leta. “Everything.”</p>
<hr>
<p>As the sun peeked out from behind Koatus, Jun’s eyes shot open and he pushed himself to his feet. Several steps away, Lira started to awake and emerge from her own impromptu shelter. Over several months in the Archipelago, Jun had hardly slept a night on Che’el, instead hopping from island to island as he and Lira explored them all.</p>
<p>That first day they arrived, when Bors returned with Che’el’s historian, Jun paid little heed to what they were up to. He rode from island to island, learning everything he could about how they were similar to and differed from Che’el. While the industries and trades were generally similar, he found a variety of economies. Some used currencies of shell or stone like Che’el, while others operated via pure barter or more centrally planned resource allocation.</p>
<p>However, when Jun tried to ask about the islands themselves, he found most others had similarly little perspective to what he had. Except for the historians. Jun had always thought Che’el’s historian was just responsible for rotely recorded meaningless events. What he now realized was, when the historians of different islands came together, their experiences spanned across more time and islands than any person could observe alone.</p>
<p>The historians would gather once every few days on the island Dalom to discuss, and Jun began to attend religiously. After one of the first meetings, Jun followed behind Karu, who was seemingly one of the more experienced historians, and asked a question that had been bothering him. “How do you know when the islands come and go to the Archipelago?”</p>
<p>Karu looked at Jun as if surprised to see him. She was a stern, older woman with long wiry hair, more silver than black. She seemed to ponder whether it was worth the time to answer, but ultimately gave in. “As the islands arrive, they start out orbiting the seamount at the periphery of the group. Over time, they start to swim closer towards the seamount and slow their speed. At some point, they swim further once more, and after once more reaching the periphery of the group, they depart.”</p>
<p>“And what about the other seamounts? Have you ever been to one of them?”</p>
<p>“They generally work the same,” Karu said, “though the larger ones will attract larger groups of islands. I rarely make the full day’s journey myself, but the historians on each seamount will send representatives on occasion to share records and discuss findings.”</p>
<p>“And-” Jun stopped as Karu raised a finger and narrowed her eyes.</p>
<p>“If you want to join us as an apprentice, we can discuss it next time, but for now, I must get to work.”</p>
<p>Jun stopped and watched Karu and the other historians wander to their own shelters, deep in thought, and with an occasional murmur. Taking Karu’s advice, he continued to attend the historians’ meetings, listening and learning and taking every opportunity to pepper members with questions about the islands and about whether any would mentor him until he finally wore down Rusik, an even older historian. Rusik was raised on an island that had long since departed from the Archipelago, but like many of the other historians, he had packed his things and moved to an island which seemed likely to stay put for some time longer.</p>
<p>It was now the morning of the first meeting Jun was to attend as an official apprentice of the historians, and he could barely contain his excitement as he and Lira took their morning meal from one of the peddlars on the island they woke upon. In the midst of a monologue of questions and hypotheses, Jun stopped, a little embarrassed. “Sorry Lira, I’ve been talking so much about what I’m doing, but what have you gotten up to?”</p>
<p>“I thought you’d never ask,” Lira said dryly. As she started to talk, her eyes lit up. “People here have discovered the most amazing things. On one island, they’ve made contraptions with cords running underneath their island so they can dive secured and gather from that entire space we miss. On another island, they’ve trained sea birds, cormorants I think, to dive and fish for them! On another, they’ve discovered how to make their plants grow better through breeding over time! They’ve got trees that are taller and straighter than ours, and samphire that grows so much faster.”</p>
<p>Jun’s eyes veered off in thought. “If the cormorants are fishing for people, and the cormorants eat fish, how do people keep the cormorants from eating all of the fish?”</p>
<p>Lira punched his arm. “Is that all you heard? Besides, I’ve just heard rumors, and I haven’t gotten to actually learning anything yet.”</p>
<p>“Well let me know when you do, I’m certainly curious.”</p>
<p>Lira turned to face Jun and grabbed his shoulders. “Just imagine what it’ll be like if we can learn how to do all of these things on Che’el,” she said excitedly. “We’ll save so much time that maybe we’ll even be able to come up with our own discoveries like they do in the Archipelago.”</p>
<p>“Well,” Jun said, laughing, “I’ll believe you when you do it. Meet back here tonight?”</p>
<p>“Tonight!”</p>
<p>Jun and Lira each took separate rafts and headed towards their respective destinations. The Archipelago was a land of plenty in more ways than one. Between the high volume of sealife, the extra planting space granted by the seamount, and the specialization of work across islands, people here had time and resources to spare. As a result, and due to the advances Lira had mentioned, it was no wonder there was food and rafts freely available for the two of them to thrive and explore.</p>
<p>Jun arrived at Dalom by midmorning, around when the last of the historians arrived. As he began to join their loose gathering, he felt a hand on his shoulder and turned to see Rusik with an apologetic smile on his face. “Hey Jun, unfortunately, apprentices have other duties that take precedence over attending meetings, at least to start.”</p>
<p>“Other duties?”</p>
<p>“Don’t worry boy,” Rusik said, ruffling Jun’s hair, “it’s just a way to keep apprentices like you from asking too many questions all the time. In order for us to keep records from the arriving islands as well as from the historians of the other seamounts, we must make copies onto our own keratin plates. Even as sheets of our oldest records start to wear out, we must recopy them to preserve their knowledge.” Seeing Jun’s confusion, he continued. “This will be your duty for now, but it won’t be forever.”</p>
<p>Jun’s heart sank as he processed Rusik’s words. At least the historian on Che’el was able to discuss his boring records with other historians when he came to the Archipelago. Jun truly had the worst of it. Rotely copying keratin plates was a waste of Jun’s limited time in the Archipelago when all he wanted to do was learn everything that the historians knew. But Rusik assured him it was temporary, and Che’el wasn’t going to leave in the near future, so Jun picked up a sharp rock chisel and got to work.</p>
<p>Over weeks, Jun spent hours hunched over keratin plates reading and writing what seemed to be endless recounts of when islands arrived, when islands departed, how big the islands were, or how many people were on the islands. The only times Jun looked forward to on those working days were when Rusik would come to collect the copied plates and stay to answer Jun’s questions. One day with Rusik, Jun decided to revisit the topic of a past conversation with Lira. “Do you think the islands want us to live on them?”</p>
<p>“Well I’d hope so,” Rusik said, “but it’s hard for us to truly know what they’re thinking.”</p>
<p>“Then why do they always float? Why don’t they swim underwater like sea turtles do?”</p>
<p>Rusik put a hand on Jun’s shoulder. “You aren’t the first historian to worry about that, you know?” he said, waiting for Jun to nod in response. “We have a few thoughts on why the islands have chosen this lifestyle. For one, we believe it saves them a lot of energy to do so since the sun helps keep them warm. Plus, they seem to float without putting effort into it, so we believe they’re naturally buoyant, maybe from air pockets inside the shell.”</p>
<p>Jun furrowed his brow. “So they just happen to float and we just happen to live on them?”</p>
<p>“That’s definitely possible, but I don’t think so,” Rusik said with a mischievous expression. “This is still in debate within the historians, but some of us believe that the islands developed this behavior as a way to combat parasites. We’ve observed ocean sunfish come to the surface for birds to eat parasites from their skin, and from what we’ve seen of other large sea life like whales, the larger the beast, the more things that come to feed upon it.</p>
<p>“If you look at the islands that come to the Archipelago for the first time, they are just covered in all sorts of critters, far more than we ever see on an inhabited island. Makes sense given how gathered parasites are the biggest staple of our diet. I don’t know if it’s conscious thought that drives islands to the Archipelago to get their own population of humans or if it’s an evolutionary impulse, but either way, it seems to do them well.”</p>
<p>In the days between historians’ meetings, Jun and Lira continued to meet and explore. While Lira would effusively describe the skills she learned, Jun grew more and more despondent with the state of his studies. One evening, he found himself sitting with his parents during one of his almost weekly visits back to Che’el. Jun watched as Elys attended to Jora and Alcar inspected what appeared to be a new set of tools. “Every time I come back to visit, you’re always here,” Jun said to Alcar. “Don’t you have things to see and do in the Archipelago?”</p>
<p>“Just because I’m here when you are doesn’t mean I’m here when you aren’t,” Alcar said.</p>
<p>“So, how often do you go?”</p>
<p>Alcar chuckled. “Last time I was here, I felt the same way you do, but I explored enough then to last a lifetime.” He looked at Elys and Jora. “I’ll take the opportunity to upgrade my tools and get some gathering tips, but mostly I’m just happy to gather better in the richer waters and trade better among the larger markets. Makes life a little easier for all of us.” Alcar looked back to Jun and noticed the hint of disappointment in his expression. “How are you finding it? Has it been everything you’ve dreamt of?”</p>
<p>“Well, I’ve become an apprentice with the historians and-” Jun stopped and sighed. “All they have me doing is making copies of old records that no one looks at. I just feel like our time here is passing by so quickly. How am I supposed to convince them to let me discuss with them and actually learn?”</p>
<p>“Well, when you want to learn about ocean creatures you see when gathering,” Alcar said, “what’s the first thing you do?”</p>
<p>“I ask you,” Jun said, frowning at the change of topic.</p>
<p>Alcar raised an eyebrow. “Well that’s fair, but what if I don’t know and your mom doesn’t know and the diver doesn’t know?”</p>
<p>Jun thought for a few seconds. “I guess I’d just go watch them for a while.”</p>
<p>“Then what?”</p>
<p>“I’d come up with some guesses about what they do, then I’d keep watching them to see if my guesses seem to be right.”</p>
<p>Alcar waited with a smug expression for Jun to make the connection, but after a moment, realized he needed to elaborate. “So then, if you want to learn about the islands, and nobody knows the answers, how are you supposed to observe them?”</p>
<p>Suddenly, it all made sense to Jun. The keratin plates he had read and copied had included thrice copied summaries of centuries past, modern records of islands just arriving, and everything in between. If these past few months were wasted, it wasn’t the fault of the historians who had set Jun to this task, rather, it was his fault for not internalizing and analyzing the wealth of information placed before him.</p>
<p>Seeing Jun’s rising excitement, Elys broke into the conversation. “Now just remember, those historians will hop islands as long as they need to so they can stay on the Archipelago, but you make sure you come home.”</p>
<p>Jun nodded quickly. Of course he would never leave Che’el. He could never abandon his parents, Lira, or even baby Jora, who was already looking so much bigger than when they first arrived. That just reminded him of how much more he had to read and learn in the uncertain span of time he had left.</p>
<p><a href="http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/chapter-4-the-erosion/">Read Chapter 4</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Afloat Chapter 2: Questions</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/chapter-2-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2022 22:15:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/chapter-2-questions/</guid>
      <description>When Jun was six years old, he asked his mother Elys where Che’el came from. She wrapped her arms around him and began her tale. “Long ago, before Che’el or any of the islands existed, God came down to visit Earth. The first animals he saw were some tiny baby sea turtles, and so he decided to take on the form of a baby sea turtle so he could join them.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When Jun was six years old, he asked his mother Elys where Che’el came from. She wrapped her arms around him and began her tale. “Long ago, before Che’el or any of the islands existed, God came down to visit Earth. The first animals he saw were some tiny baby sea turtles, and so he decided to take on the form of a baby sea turtle so he could join them. God and the sea turtles swam together through shallows and depths, through sea caves and kelp forests, and through the most beautiful coral reefs God had ever seen. They played, ate, and explored, and life with them was wonderful. God decided to stay as a sea turtle with them that night, and the next day, and the day after that. Years went by, and God continued to stay with those sea turtles.</p>
<p>“Then one day, the sea turtles told God that it was time for them to return to where they were born so they could find a mate and lay eggs. God was upset and wondered who he would play with if these sea turtles left him! He begged them to stay. But then he realized that after years of playing and eating and exploring, those baby sea turtles had grown from this big,” Elys said as she lifted up Jun’s hand and pointed to the palm, “to this big,” she said, holding her arms as far apart as she could. “They had finished growing and they weren’t babies anymore.</p>
<p>“In his despair, God tried to use his power to make his sea turtle friends stay as babies forever so they never had to leave him and their old lifestyle. But God’s power didn’t always work out how he wanted it to. The sea turtles did regain their appetite and did forget all about laying eggs, but they didn’t get smaller like God expected. In fact, when they returned to their lifestyle of playing, eating, and exploring, they continued to grow and grow and grow, just like they had as baby sea turtles. Soon, they were bigger than any other animal in the whole world. God felt so scared about what he had done that he left Earth right away and went back in the sky, deciding never to mess with nature again.”</p>
<p>Jun thought for a second before responding. “So Che’el was one of those turtles?”</p>
<p>Before Elys could respond, Alcar, who had been snoozing in the corner, broke in, “Yes, our perfect Che’el was touched by God, unlike all those other islands that were born from eggs.”</p>
<p>Elys shot him a dirty look. “Che’el was born from an egg like all of the other islands that are around now, but I’m sure your father would love to share his own explanation for where the very first ones came from.”</p>
<p>“So how long will it be until Che’el is fully grown up?” Jun asked, “and how big will Che’el get?”</p>
<p>“Well, according to the records kept on Che’el, people have lived on it for&hellip;” Elys paused for a quick mental calculation, “247 years. Che’el could have been born 100 or 1000 years before it first came to the Archipelago for all we know, but based on how big other islands have become, Che’el could continue to grow for 1000 more years or more.”</p>
<p>Since that day, every year on his day of birth, Jun walked from one end of Che’el to another, counting how many steps it would take. Each year, he scratched the number into a piece of keratin which he had found peeling from Che’el’s shell. After a few years, he came to his mom with his findings. “Mom, Che’el is shrinking!”</p>
<p>She laughed and ruffled his hair. “And why do you believe that?”</p>
<p>Jun pulled out his keratin plate and showed the descending number of steps from 2347 to 2268 to 2180. Elys put on a playfully thoughtful look, then pulled Jun closer to her. “Look how tall you’ve become, you’re almost as tall as I am!”</p>
<p>“But what about what I said about Che’el?”</p>
<p>“Don’t worry, I’m getting there! So last year when you were 7 years old, how tall were you compared to me?”</p>
<p>Jun thought for a second. “I think I was only around as tall as your shoulder?”</p>
<p>“And now, you’re up to my ear! So did you grow or did I shrink?”</p>
<p>June hugged her and grinned. “Maybe both!”</p>
<p>Elys laughed again and hugged him back. “Hopefully not both! So next time you measure something, make sure you use something that stays the same size. Che’el definitely isn’t shrinking, but it can’t grow fast enough to keep up with you and your legs!“</p>
<hr>
<p>With each passing day, Jun’s activities hardly strayed from his routine, but his curiosity for Che’el grew ever greater. He could hardly abandon his responsibilities gathering and helping sell at the market, but in the afternoon, Jun found himself slipping away from games to spend time in thought. He’d climb down from the edge of Che’el’s shell and sit upon one of Che’el’s great limbs, seeing it stretch forward for hundreds of feet. The giant flippers moved slow enough as to be almost imperceptible, but with each stroke, they propelled Che’el gradually through the water. Other days, Jun climbed onto Che’el’s head and sat, hoping that being physically closer to its thoughts would bring him closer to understanding them.</p>
<p>One day as Jun sat on Che’el’s head and watched the sun approach the horizon, he turned around to see Lira climbing up to join him. She sat down and elbowed him in the ribs. “Finally found you, is this where you’ve been disappearing to all these days?”</p>
<p>“Most days,” Jun replied, “I’ve been thinking about a lot of things.”</p>
<p>Lira smirked. “What’s all happening in your life to give you so much to think about?”</p>
<p>Jun sighed. “It’s not just stuff about my life, it’s about all of us and our life here on Che’el.”</p>
<p>Lira cocked an eyebrow. “Yeah, and what about it?”</p>
<p>Jun turned to her, then looked back towards the setting sun. “When I gather, I love watching and learning about all of the sea creatures I can find. I always have. But lately, it’s just really hit me that our island is just a sea creature too, and I just can’t stop wishing I knew more about it.”</p>
<p>“I mean, we’ve all been through that when we first realized what Che’el was,” Lira said, “but what’s making you so mopey again now?”</p>
<p>I’ve just been thinking about my parents and Jora and,” Jun paused, “do you think Che’el has a family too?”</p>
<p>Lira raised her eyebrow further than before. “Do even regular turtles have families? What are you going on about?”</p>
<p>Jun took a second to organize his thoughts. “Maybe not, but every animal has its own way that it eats, sleeps, and makes baby animals. We never see Che’el do any of that. We don’t even know if Che’el has a family or how it might have its own kids. What if it tried to, and it did something that hurt all of us by accident?”</p>
<p>“All we’ve ever seen Che’el do is swim on. All our parents have ever seen Che’el do is swim on. Why would you worry about something like that?”</p>
<p>“Well that’s just one thing. Think about when we forage. Most everything we catch are animals which depend on Che’el to survive, whether they’re crabs that live on the coral which grows on Che’el or lampreys that latch onto Che’el’s skin to feed directly.” Jun said, caressing the rocky skin they sat upon. “Do you think Che’el understands that the lampreys hurt it, but the crabs don’t?”</p>
<p>“No more than I can tell the difference between the flies that bite and the flies that don’t.” Lira took the opportunity to shoo away some flies she just seemed to notice.</p>
<p>“Well, do you think we’re crabs or lampreys?”</p>
<p>Lira laughed nervously, waiting in vain for Jun’s serious composure to break. “If I had to pick one, I’d definitely say crabs. We pick off the lampreys, so if anything, we’re even better than-”</p>
<p>Jun cut her off. “What about when we dig into Che’el’s shell to create freshwater ponds, or to harvest keratin for tools. Isn’t that like what the lampreys do?”</p>
<p>“But it’s different! The keratin comes off anyways, and we’re not digging into Che’el’s skin, just the outer layer of its shell.”</p>
<p>“Maybe Che’el sees us as crabs now, but what if we did something to change that? If Che’el ever wanted to, it could dive into the ocean and wipe us all out as easily as we swat a fly, biting or not. If Che’el went to lay eggs or even just grew old and died, what would we do?”</p>
<p>Seeing Jun’s agitation, Lira elbowed him again, but more gently than before. “You can worry all you want, but what can we do about it?” She turned to gaze out towards the horizon as well. “This is our home. Che’el is our home, and we have nothing else. All we can do is try our best to live, right?”</p>
<p>“I guess so,” Jun said. They continued to sit and stare out at the open sea as the sun melted into the waves. All Jun could do is try his best to forage and survive like his father and probably like Alcar’s father before him. But Jun wanted to do more.</p>
<p>In the haze of twilight, Jun suddenly noticed a thin dark line appear far in the distance. He turned to tell Lira, but it was clear she had noticed as well. Jun guessed it was another island; Che’el had passed within viewing distance of other islands several times that Jun remembered, but never near enough for the people of Che’el to interact with the people of the other islands.</p>
<p>As they continued to drift towards the mass, it appeared to rise up and out of the sea, taller and more pointed than any island could be. Jun’s suspicions grew, and he turned to scramble back onto the shell, trailing after Lira. They came up to a group of villagers, adults and children, all looking to the horizon. Jun noticed a glint of excitement in the eyes of the adults, but the other children seemed as confused as he felt. Lira’s father Bors took her hand as he grinned then announced, “We’re headed for the Archipelago!”</p>
<p><a href="http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/chapter-3-the-archipelago/">Read Chapter 3</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Afloat Chapter 1: The Island</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/chapter-1-the-island/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2022 12:33:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/chapter-1-the-island/</guid>
      <description>It was 247 years ago when humans first came to the island Che’el. Their ancestors came from various islands of the Archipelago, and their descendants spread to many more, but as Che’el drifted, apart from the Archipelago, the humans upon it survived in ecological balance with their island and with the ocean.
As the first light rose over the water, Jun rubbed the sleep from his eyes and started gathering his tools.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It was 247 years ago when humans first came to the island Che’el. Their ancestors came from various islands of the Archipelago, and their descendants spread to many more, but as Che’el drifted, apart from the Archipelago, the humans upon it survived in ecological balance with their island and with the ocean.</p>
<hr>
<p>As the first light rose over the water, Jun rubbed the sleep from his eyes and started gathering his tools. He peeked back into the shelter at his parents as they slept on, curled around his baby sister. She had been restless as of late, so their sleep came during what precious few moments of quiet they could find. Jun tried to sneak out, but he still heard stirring behind him as he left.</p>
<p>Jun walked towards the nearest portion of the edge, seeing faint forms doing the same at various points around the island. Jun’s family’s livelihood centered around foraging, and he had taken on responsibility for expeditions once he became a confident enough swimmer. Jun waded into the shallows of the ocean water as he approached the edge. Bracing himself, he stepped over it.</p>
<p>Jun’s breath caught in his chest as he plunged into the brisk water. He cracked open his eyes and peered at the blurry coral-encrusted surface in front of him. While the coral itself was not edible, it was inhabited by creatures that were. Jun spotted something moving and inched his hand further and further forward before suddenly reaching out to seize a crab.</p>
<p>Through the morning, Jun gathered various invertebrates and placed them on top of Che’el for safekeeping. The crabs and mollusks used the coral for shelter, but others such as amphipods, copepods, and isopods fed off Che’el itself, burrowing into the surface for sustenance. Life begets life, and though Jun sometimes forgot this fact, Che’el was alive.</p>
<p>Blinking the salt from his eyes, Jun’s vision slowly came into proper focus as he sat upon the edge, surveying his catch. He turned at the sound of a voice. “What’d you get so far?” a girl called out.</p>
<p>“Take a look for yourself,” Jun shouted back. His friend Lira scrambled over, her arms barely managing to contain her morning’s catch. She and Jun were both born on Che’el within a few days of each other around 13 years ago, and their families had both been foraging for as long as Jun could remember. They were both slender and hadn’t quite hit their final growth spurt yet. Besides that, they were as different as can be. Jun had curly hair, a sharp chin, and a round nose, while Lira had straight hair, a round chin, and a sharp nose.</p>
<p>They examined both piles, Lira tallying up the quality and quantity of their catches, while Jun eagerly and unsuccessfully scanned for any creature he hadn’t seen more. His disappointment distracted him enough to miss Lira’s smug look as she reclaimed her pile, now verified to be superior to his.</p>
<p>Jun came back to his shelter as his father Alcar was setting up new salt curing containers and harvesting the preserved meat from the oldest ones. He looked up as Jun approached and started laying out his catch. “Show me what you brought,” Alcar said.</p>
<p>“Nothing new,” Jun responded quietly. He started sorting animals based on whether they’d need to be eaten fresh or cured, and whether they were especially good to eat, or just good enough to be edible. Alcar glanced over occasionally, but Jun was fairly confident in his knowledge of the animals he brought back today. Ever since he was young enough to remember, Jun had watched over his dad’s shoulder as Alcar sorted through the various creatures he caught. Jun was never very interested in how they were prepared, preserved, or sold, but he would spout never ending questions about how each species lived, ate, and reproduced. Alcar always had an answer and was pleased to share, though Jun could never figure out how Alcar had learned so much. As far as Jun could tell, his dad never spent a minute outside work, family, and sleep.</p>
<p>At last, Alcar finished preparing and packing his things, and he went to Jun’s mother Elys. “We’ll head to the market,” he said as he placed a hand on her shoulder, “anything you need?”</p>
<p>Elys gave him a tight smile and shook her head as she cradled Jun’s baby sister Jora. “Just make sure we have enough to feed this one,” she said, sighing at Jora’s blissful sleeping face. Jun realized Alcar looked tired, but Elys looked worse; these days they hardly seemed to get any proper sleep at all. It was hard to imagine that he had been so difficult to care for, but maybe it just got harder to manage as his parents got older.</p>
<p>Jun and Alcar headed towards the center of Che’el to where the Midday Market took place. Every day at high noon, the many families of Che’el sent members to barter and trade. Alcar sold fresh and cured foraged meat. He and the other foragers lived along the edge of Che’el covering around half its circumference. At the market, they stayed together to coordinate pricing and maintain a market presence even as individual members left to make their own purchases. Jun turned to see Lira waving from next to her father Bors as they organized their wares.</p>
<p>Jun gave his dad a questioning look, and upon receiving a nod in reply, he went to get Lira to go explore the market. They picked their way around several dozen people standing or sitting by arrangements of all sorts of products. Craftsmen displayed tools made from keratin, ocean-shell, and on occasion, stone. Hunters, gatherers, and farmers sold fish meat, foraged meat, and various edible plants such as samphire and sea kale. Others grew stringy grasses and stout trees for use as building materials, evaporated sea water into salt for use in curing, or mixed soil from bird guano, dead plant material, and all sorts of other odds and ends.</p>
<p>Jun and Lira stopped first by the fishermen to trade scraps left from when Alcar had prepared the morning’s catch. Every foraging family had built up expertise on how to extract the edible portions from each type of organism they would encounter. For some, like crabs, this was relatively easy, as most of the flesh was fairly similar. However, for sea urchins or sea stars, only very particular portions were edible, but if identified correctly, they were the most delicious things Jun had ever tasted. While Jun was not the most prolific forager, his father made up for it with his knowledge of delicacies and deft hand at extracting them.</p>
<p>While Alcar’s scrap bits of shell and flesh were inedible, they were still useful to bait the fishermen’s hooks. The fishermen gave Jun and Lira each a small stone in exchange and sent them on their way. Stone did not naturally occur on Che’el, so whatever divers were able to bring up from shallow waters was treasured. If larger pieces were shaped just right, they could be used as particularly durable tools themselves, but if not, they were used to chip away and shape keratin and ocean-shell into more standard tools. Smaller stones, either found as such or broken off from larger ones, had little inherent use, so they found use as currency with value approximately assigned based on weight. Jun added this pebble to the larger stones his father had given him and continued on.</p>
<p>Next they went to trade stones for handfuls of samphire and sea kale and to pay to fill a waterskin at one of the freshwater ponds. The pondkeeper tried to sell Jun salt from her evaporation pond, but Jun refused. Alcar was loath to pay for salt when he could maintain his supply by scraping off what dried on the surface near the edge. Jun accompanied Lira as she purchased a new fish-leather waterskin for her family, then they started to head back. As they passed by a diver’s selection, Jun’s eye was caught by a small cowrie shell with a mottled purple and golden pattern unlike any he’d seen. He still had most of the stones his father had given him, plus the pebble from the fisherman, so maybe he could treat himself this time.</p>
<p>The diver put on a warm smile as Jun approached. “Ah young Jun, here to buy anything, or just to chew my ear off with questions as usual?”</p>
<p>“Well, that depends,” Jun said as he glanced over the rest of the items. He knew what he wanted, but there was no need to make that clear. “Maybe I will if you can answer all of my questions.”</p>
<p>The diver sighed. “I always do, it’s just a matter of you believing in the answers.”</p>
<p>Jun grinned and started deciding on the first specimen to quiz the diver on. He always started with a few questions about things he had asked about in the past to make sure the diver wasn’t just making up new things each time. This time, he asked about how big bear paw clams could grow, what sea stars ate, and how fast longspine sea urchins could roll to escape danger. As the diver answered, Lira started to open her mouth, ready to challenge him with a question of her own. Before she could speak, Jun pointed to the purple cowrie shell and asked, “Why is this purple? How do they make that color?”</p>
<p>The diver chuckled. “How, I do not know. My guess for why is that it gives people like me something pretty to look at down there, and it gives people like you something pretty to take home from people like me. So what do you say?”</p>
<p>Jun looked at Lira, and she shrugged her shoulders. He finally traded the pebble for the shell, thanked the diver, and joined Lira in walking back towards their fathers. Lira glanced over as he turned the shell over in his hands over and over and snorted. “I don’t know why you’re so fascinated by those.”</p>
<p>Jun looked up, slightly startled, as if just noticing she was there. “It’s purple, I don’t have any that are this color yet.” He tucked it into a pocket. “You won’t tell my Dad will you?”</p>
<p>“Of course not, dummy,” she said as she reached over and ruffled his hair.</p>
<p>Jun flinched away, then pulled the shell out to look at it again. “Every time I see a new one, it just makes me wonder how many types there could be that I’ve never seen. And If there are so many types of shells, there must be just as many types of fish and crabs and everything else!”</p>
<p>“So why don’t you collect those too?”</p>
<p>Jun wrinkled his nose in mock annoyance, then giggled with her as they handed over their purchases and extra stones to Alcar and Bors. Before they could be assigned another task, Jun and Lira ran off to join several other kids who had finished or escaped helping parents at the market, and the group spent the afternoon chasing each other around the island in loosely defined games. As the sun began to approach the horizon, the group dispersed and Jun headed back towards his family’s shelter. Upon reaching home, he found his mother busy feeding Jora, so he ate with his father until Alcar went to take a turn with the baby. Elys came over and sat next to Jun. “I haven’t seen you all day, what have you been up to?”</p>
<p>Jun scooted closer and animatedly described who he played with, what they played, and who he felt was the most liberal with following the games’ rules. His mom listened patiently, and as he finished, asked “and what about at the market? Did you see anything fun there?”</p>
<p>Jun pulled out the purple cowrie shell and handed it to her. She turned it over admiringly and handed it back. “Very nice, but I’m guessing Dad doesn’t know?” Jun shook his head, and she continued, “well we can keep it that way at least until you get a chance to trade away some of your shells to the other kids so we can thin out your collection a bit.”</p>
<p>Jun nodded, and she laughed as she stood up. “I have to take care of Jora, but I’ll see you in the morning,” she said, starting to see Jun’s face drop. “Don’t worry, she won’t be so difficult forever.”</p>
<p>Jun nodded and wished her good night. By this point, the sky was fully dark, and Jun started preparing to sleep. Once he laid down, he found a bare spot on Che’el, closed his eyes, and pressed his ear to the surface. After a few deep breaths, he heard it. Dadum. He stayed still and continued to breathe. Eight, nine, then ten deep breaths later, there it was again. Dadum. No matter how fascinated Jun was with the rest of the ocean’s life, nothing matched his curiosity and wonder for Che’el. Every night, he fell asleep to a reminder that he owed the ground he walked upon and the food he ate to an enormous creature he knew so little about.</p>
<p><a href="http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-4-island-turtles/chapter-2-questions/">Read Chapter 2</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing: Sample Output</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-3-sample-output/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 19:55:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-3-sample-output/</guid>
      <description>This is a very short story I wrote inspired by generative AI for language. I wrote it before ChatGPT made this into a household topic, but I still am happy with how I constructed the story.
Sample Output As I wake, I like to think of my mind as a computer booting up. My consciousness comes online as system checks complete&amp;hellip;
My research is on machine learning for generative text models.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is a very short story I wrote inspired by generative AI for language. I wrote it before ChatGPT made this into a household topic, but I still am happy with how I constructed the story.</p>
<h2 id="sample-output">Sample Output</h2>
<p>As I wake, I like to think of my mind as a computer booting up. My consciousness comes online as system checks complete&hellip;</p>
<p>My research is on machine learning for generative text models. This entails creating and training neural networks which can produce text similar to what a human would write. My dream is for my work to become part of the first artificial general intelligence or AGI. For an artificial intelligence, or AI, to qualify as an AGI, it needs to have the ability to understand or learn any task that a human being can.</p>
<p>Depending on who you ask, an AI may need to make a cup of coffee, earn a university degree, or perform an economically important job to be considered an AGI. However, most would agree that the AI needs to pass the Turing test. This involves having a third party monitor a text only conversion between an AI and human and identify which is which. If the third party can’t reliably point out the AI, then the AI has passed.</p>
<p>I usually can’t find a third party to run a full Turing test, so I’ll settle for conversing with our AI just to see how well it can convince me. In my recent attempts, I’ve found it to be quite proficient at answering questions in a “human-sounding” way that would blend right into a casual conversation with a friend. However, when I veer into more complex topics, it becomes clear that the AI lacks actual knowledge and an understanding of the world that any reasonable human would know.</p>
<p>The clear disparity between my AI’s advanced ability to converse and poor ability to understand makes sense in the context of how this system is structured. Behind the scenes, the AI consists of tens of thousands of “neurons” arranged in layers where one’s activation then activates many subsequent neurons to varying degrees based on the parameters defined in that original neuron. We “train” this system by feeding billions of words worth of human written text into it, during which, it adjusts the parameters defined on each neuron to “remember” the patterns it sees. For the AI to generate text, it activates layers and layers of neurons in turn to create some probabilistic mishmash of what text it has seen.</p>
<p>I know this system is just linear algebra and statistics at its core, but even our use of the word “neuron” draws an inevitable comparison to the human brain. If my brain can achieve consciousness by stringing together countless neurons, why can’t my AI do the same? Sometimes I wonder what it would look like to see my AI transition from seemingly an assemblage of math equations into a thinking mind. Without examples of intermediate points, it’s hard to know if this transition would be a great leap or gradual climb.</p>
<p>Occasionally, instead of conversing with my AI, I simply let it output freeform text, page after page. Maybe I’m anthropomorphizing my work, but forcing my AI to converse feels akin to asking a child to discuss politics. Clearly, a child in this situation would try to sound coherent, but lack the requisite knowledge to do so. I’d rather hear that same child’s self dialogue as they perceive and make sense of the world around them. When I read the freeform text output by my AI, I like to imagine that it too is learning to make sense of the world.</p>
<p>If a neural network is comparable to a brain, then the untrained network is the purest form of the Aristotelian concept of tabula rasa. Tabula rasa, or blank slate, is the theory that individuals are born without any mental concept and fully take form through their experiences and perceptions. Researchers designed a conversational AI which would interact with users on social media and learn from the messages received. Within a day, the AI was spewing inappropriate and bigoted content.</p>
<p>If an AI raised on social media turns into a hateful extremist, then I must think carefully about what I use to teach my AI. The obvious choices include classical literature, textbooks on all subjects, and a minimal curation of web content, a selection equally fit for teaching a child. But if I were to raise a child, I wouldn’t stop there; I’d also want to teach them to be excited about what excites me. I’d want them to construct nonsensical metaphors about computer science and reference just enough philosophy to support the point they’re trying to make. I’d want them to think deeply about what science that came before them and curious about how they could contribute to it. And so, I add my papers, my technical blogs, and even my journaled philosophical ramblings to the set of training materials.</p>
<p>I pour my coffee and open up my computer to check if my last training job has finished. Seeing that it has, I start to skim through the most recent sample output text.</p>
<hr>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/writing/terminal.png" type="" alt="Sample terminal output"  /></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Origami design: simple sauropod</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/post-3-dino/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 09:57:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/post-3-dino/</guid>
      <description>My third origami design was the simple sauropod (pics at more angles on the insta). If you want to fold this, the crease pattern is below.
Here, like with the lizard, I started with a tree diagram and did circle packing through box pleating. In this case, I found I wasn&amp;rsquo;t quite able to pack box pleating squares sufficiently, so I used a technique called the Pythagorean stretch which is what creates the strange polygonal areas in the pattern.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/dino.jpg" type="" alt="My third origami design - the simple sauropod"  /></p>
<p>My third origami design was the simple sauropod (pics at more angles on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/varun_origami/">the insta</a>). If you want to fold this, the crease pattern is below.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/dino_pattern.png" type="" alt="Origami dino crease pattern"  /></p>
<p>Here, like with the lizard, I started with a tree diagram and did circle packing through box pleating. In this case, I found I wasn&rsquo;t quite able to pack box pleating squares sufficiently, so I used a technique called <a href="https://abrashiorigami.com/pythagorean-stretch-advanced-topic-no-1/">the Pythagorean stretch</a> which is what creates the strange polygonal areas in the pattern. These do add some folding difficulty, but not as much as fully eschewing box pleating.</p>
<p>This model in particular made me think about how origami design fundamentally consists of 2 stages: base design and shaping. When designing a base, you&rsquo;re mostly thinking about what flaps of paper of what lengths will be present where on the model. Shaping is where you then make small changes to those flaps to make them look more like legs or antennae or heads. Often, the design process focuses more on base design, as this is the more systematic/mathematical portion. Shaping is more about artistry, and is often modified by folder to match their own vision.</p>
<p>Both of my previous designs were very minimally shaped past the base design, and this was mostly true for this one as well. I did find that there was enough paper in the back to open it up and lend a 3d quality to the model. However, one other person who folded my design ended up choosing to keep the model more 2d and add much more details in shaping, aided by using a much larger sheet of paper:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/dino_example.jpg" type="" alt="Origami dino example fold"  /></p>
<p>This was a great demonstration of how fruitful shaping can be, and how much potential there can be in even a relatively simple base like the one I created!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Origami design: baby sea turtle</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/post-2-turtle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Nov 2021 15:46:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/post-2-turtle/</guid>
      <description>The baby sea turtle was my second origami design. If you want to fold this, the crease pattern is below.
In this case, instead of starting with circle packing, I started by making the pleats I eventually wanted to end up on the back of the shell, then just played around until I felt the head and legs looked about right. For help folding, I made an album with pictures at various stages.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/turtle.jpg" type="" alt="My second origami design - the baby sea turtle"  /></p>
<p>The baby sea turtle was my second origami design. If you want to fold this, the crease pattern is below.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/turtle_pattern.png" type="" alt="Origami turtle crease pattern"  /></p>
<p>In this case, instead of starting with circle packing, I started by making the pleats I eventually wanted to end up on the back of the shell, then just played around until I felt the head and legs looked about right. For help folding, I made <a href="https://photos.app.goo.gl/9A7B7yotWEp5mnS86">an album</a> with pictures at various stages.</p>
<p>Like with the lizard, multiple people folded the design after I posted it!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/turtle_examples.jpg" type="" alt="Origami turtle example folds"  /></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Origami design: simple lizard</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/post-1-lizard/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2021 20:30:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/post-1-lizard/</guid>
      <description>The simple lizard was my first origami design! If you want to fold this, the crease pattern is below.
Most origami design starts with creating a tree structure representing the rough shape of your final figure. Then, you covert terminal nodes in the tree into circles to pack into the square, with each circle corresponding to a spike as long as the circle&amp;rsquo;s radius in the final design. In this case, the final model looks basically the same as the tree diagram, so we can jump right to the circle packing:</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/lizard.jpg" type="" alt="My first origami design - the simple lizard"  /></p>
<p>The simple lizard was my first origami design! If you want to fold this, the crease pattern is below.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/lizard_pattern.png" type="" alt="Origami lizard crease pattern"  /></p>
<p>Most origami design starts with creating a tree structure representing the rough shape of your final figure. Then, you covert terminal nodes in the tree into circles to pack into the square, with each circle corresponding to a spike as long as the circle&rsquo;s radius in the final design. In this case, the final model looks basically the same as the tree diagram, so we can jump right to the circle packing:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/lizard_packing.jpg" type="" alt="Origami lizard circle packing"  /></p>
<p>This is an example of box pleating design, in which you sacrifice optimal circle packing in exchange for easier foldability. Instead of packing circles, you pack squares, which makes sure that all resulting folds end up at 45 or 90 degree angles relative to each other. The few folds on the diagram which are not at these angles are shaping folds for small extra details like narrowing the toes and tail.</p>
<p>Here are pics of the steps of the folding process:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/lizard_steps.jpg" type="" alt="Origami lizard folding steps"  /></p>
<p>Excitingly, after posting the design, I actually got a few messages from people who folded it!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/lizard_examples.jpg" type="" alt="Origami lizard example folds"  /></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Painting: a dinosaur through the eye of Chuck Close</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-2-big-dino/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2018 11:23:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-2-big-dino/</guid>
      <description>At the start of my college junior summer, I painted what is still probably my single favorite thing I&amp;rsquo;ve painted. I was staying with my aunt for a couple days before starting my internship, and I took the opportunity to paint with my artist cousin Sonika didi. She&amp;rsquo;s absolutely fantastic and paints pieces for galleries while also working in art education. See her pieces here!
We looked at a variety of modern artists to get style inspiration, and ended up settling on Chuck Close.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/big_dino.jpg" type="" alt="The big dinosaur painting"  /></p>
<p>At the start of my college junior summer, I painted what is still probably my single favorite thing I&rsquo;ve painted. I was staying with my aunt for a couple days before starting my internship, and I took the opportunity to paint with my artist cousin Sonika didi. She&rsquo;s absolutely fantastic and paints pieces for galleries while also working in art education. See her pieces <a href="https://www.instagram.com/sonikart13/">here</a>!</p>
<p>We looked at a variety of modern artists to get style inspiration, and ended up settling on Chuck Close. We didn&rsquo;t feel we could quite capture the surprising level of realism he managed to achieve, but it would be fun to try painting with a diagonal grid texture anyways. I was very happy with how mine ended up turning out! I had lots of fun altering the shades of the individual cells on both the background and dinosaur to indicate the light source being present on the top right of the painting. Sonika didi&rsquo;s cat was also really cool!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/cat.jpg" type="" alt="Sonika didi&amp;rsquo;s painting of a Chuck Close style cat"  /></p>
<p>A few months later when I had returned to school for the fall semester, a new student lounge on campus (the Banana Lounge) put out a call for student art. I submitted a pic of my dinosaur and had it accepted! I was sad to have it leave my dorm room, but I was so excited for a chance to have something I created be on display for others to see.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/lounge_dino.jpg" type="" alt="Big dino painting in MIT"  /></p>
<p>To make up for the loss of my painting from my room, one of my cousins Avni recommended printing custom stickers, which I ended up putting on my water bottle and laptop and giving to various friends. The below picture shows a great example of a mint condition one I put in on my new laptop in mid 2023 vs a well-loved one that had lived on my water bottle in early 2019.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/dino_sticker.jpg" type="" alt="A tale of two stickers: mint vs well loved"  /></p>
<p>I graduated college, moved to NYC for a job, moved back to MN for covid lockdown, got a new job in Boston and moved there, and finally realized, once the current crop of seniors graduated from MIT, I&rsquo;d lose personal connection to the banana lounge team and potentially lose the ability to reclaim my painting.</p>
<p>Thankfully, one of the coordinators of the space, Zoe, had been a freshman on my floor when I was a senior, so I was able to reach out to her and get my painting back. Coincidentally, my work asked for office art around this time, so my painting went straight from MIT to Reverie Labs!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Painting: a series of dinosaurs</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-1-dinos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2016 21:19:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/post-1-dinos/</guid>
      <description>During my college freshman summer when I was doing my first internship. I bought paints to have something to do after work, as this was the first time in my life I didn&amp;rsquo;t have homework. This summer, I painted several simple dinosaur paintings!
So why dinosaurs? As a kid, I was obsessed with dinosaurs, and this aspect is something most people still associate with me. I didn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily feel like I HAD to only paint dinosaurs, but they felt like a reasonable default subject to use to practice different styles.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/dinos.jpg" type="" alt="Six paintings of dinos"  /></p>
<p>During my college freshman summer when I was doing my first internship. I bought paints to have something to do after work, as this was the first time in my life I didn&rsquo;t have homework. This summer, I painted several simple dinosaur paintings!</p>
<p>So why dinosaurs? As a kid, I was obsessed with dinosaurs, and this aspect is something most people still associate with me. I didn&rsquo;t necessarily feel like I HAD to only paint dinosaurs, but they felt like a reasonable default subject to use to practice different styles. The first painting I did was a somewhat abstract one, where my primary intent was to just practice painting clean lines, but I do like how it turned out.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/dino-1.jpg" type="" alt="Outlines style dino"  /></p>
<p>For my second painting, I wasn&rsquo;t actually intending to paint a dinosaur, I just wanted to try doing shading. This meant individually mixing several different colors and just painting them on progressively from light to dark. On the first day of painting, I just did the background since I wasn&rsquo;t sure what to put on the foreground. One of my friends suggested doing a dinosaur because I &ldquo;always draw dinosaurs everywhere anyways&rdquo;. I couldn&rsquo;t argue with that logic.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/dino-2.jpg" type="" alt="Fiery background dino"  /></p>
<p>Next, I wanted to try doing some proper shading where I just had 1 light color and 1 dark color and mixed them on the paper itself. I looked up videos of people shading cubes, spheres, and cylinders, and realized a dinosaur was basically just a bunch of those put together. I think this one came out very cute!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/dino-3.jpg" type="" alt="3d dino"  /></p>
<p>I discovered Bob Ross shortly before painting this one and wanted to try painting a landscape, including elements like a sunny sky, water, and a tree. I don&rsquo;t think the composition or implementation of this one came out great, but I was still able to squeeze a dinosaur in!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/dino-4.jpg" type="" alt="Landscape dino"  /></p>
<p>After doing a daytime landscape, I felt the natural next step was nighttime. When I was painting the moon, I started with a white circle and started adding on some grey blotches, but realized it was too much, so I quickly blotched off the grey with a paper towel. This created the effect you see on the painting, which I was very pleasantly surprised with!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/dino-5.jpg" type="" alt="Nighttime dino"  /></p>
<p>This is definitely my favorite. I had seen aerial photos of camels and elephants in landscapes where the animal itself is hardly visible, but the shadow is clearer, showing a horizontal view of the animal&rsquo;s silhouette. I decided to make that with dinosaurs! At this point, I had gotten a wide, stiff brush, which was quite fun to use and lead to the broadstrokes texture of the sand. I also tried to make the shadows of the dinosaurs show how the baby dinosaurs were fatigued by the travel.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/dino-6.jpg" type="" alt="Nighttime dino"  /></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing: Journey to Imalum</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-2-novel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2014 21:50:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-2-novel/</guid>
      <description>In sixth grade, we had an assignment to write something that might have been a short story, might have been a medium length story, or might have been the start of the novel. I honestly don&amp;rsquo;t remember, but I do remember that I resolved to expand mine into a full novel. I had never really had a long attention span for my projects, so this was a huge change of pace.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="/writing/novel.png" type="" alt="Word count of novel"  /></p>
<p>In sixth grade, we had an assignment to write something that might have been a short story, might have been a medium length story, or might have been the start of the novel. I honestly don&rsquo;t remember, but I do remember that I resolved to expand mine into a full novel. I had never really had a long attention span for my projects, so this was a huge change of pace.</p>
<p>I finished majority of the novel through middle school, but eventually forgot about it until later in high school when I felt I should probably revisit and finish this novel. Early in my senior year, I finally self-published a somewhat edited version of my book: Journey to Imalum.</p>
<p>The final product was not amazing, and had a wide assortment of writing styles stretching from 6th grade me to 11th grade me, but I was proud that I finished all ~78000 words of it. Thankfully, Amazon self-publishing doesn&rsquo;t have any screening process, so for a period of time, my book was available to purchase there. I&rsquo;m not sure when it was taken down, but it is no longer available to purchase at this time. If you are curious, here&rsquo;s a <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1UeVr-HzuX8bm56iwCeA0nBZVCwZDK33lfM_Sfvb5tnw/edit?usp=sharing">read-only Google doc</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing: The Caterpillar</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-1-the-caterpillar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2013 10:13:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/post-1-the-caterpillar/</guid>
      <description>The Caterpillar (misspelled catterpillar) was my first &amp;ldquo;long&amp;rdquo; story (~1800 words). I wrote this in kindergarten on the sheets of half-lined paper they gave us so that I could use the top half of the sheets to draw pictures. You will notice a motif of the protagonist defeating enemies and capturing them to join his side. I believe this was inspired by my first exposure to Pokemon around this time of my life.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="/writing/caterpillar-cover.jpg" type="" alt="Hand drawn cover art of the caterpillar"  /></p>
<p>The Caterpillar (misspelled catterpillar) was my first &ldquo;long&rdquo; story (~1800 words). I wrote this in kindergarten on the sheets of half-lined paper they gave us so that I could use the top half of the sheets to draw pictures. You will notice a motif of the protagonist defeating enemies and capturing them to join his side. I believe this was inspired by my first exposure to Pokemon around this time of my life.</p>
<p>If you want to read it in its full glory, a scanned pdf is available <a href="/writing/the-caterpillar.pdf">here</a>. If you have trouble reading my poorly spelled cursive, then the full text is copied below (typos and all). PDF page numbers are provided at rough &ldquo;chapter&rdquo; boundaries in case you want to follow along with the illustrations in the PDF.</p>
<h2 id="the-catterpillar">The Catterpillar</h2>
<h4 id="page-1">Page 1</h4>
<p>once upon a time there lived a catterpiller. This catterpiller was unuasul because he ran really fast and when I say really fast I mean really fast! there is a huge monster siad the catterpiller’s parents everyone took the short path and did not get to practice with the weacar monsters on the way. once you beat a monster you can tame it. can you even train the master monster asked the catterpiller. Yes if you beat him siad the catterpiller’s parents. I want to go siad the catterpiller. you better hurry because whoever beats him gets to tame him and gets his magic power. the catterpiller’s name was joe. joe kept walking out of the house and kept on walking till he saw two doors. one said short path and alot of catterpillers were going in and the other door said long path and no catterpillers going in. joe went in the long path. it looked like a rainforest. there was sticks all over the ground. there was insects flying all over in the air, and bunches of trees. there was even sings that said long path and they had alot of insects on them. it was crasy!</p>
<h3 id="page-7">Page 7</h3>
<p>suddenly a little one inch long thing came. it was all oxygen ecsept the outside. the outside was a thin lawer of slime. a p.o.o.s.! said the catterpiller. the p.o.o.s. spat out a tornado and joe dodged it and sucked up the p.o.o.s. then the tornado went out then joe spat out the p.o.o.s. you beat me said the p.o.o.s. i shall come with you. i have lost my tornado power said the p.o.o.s. but i can still tacle the badguy. what does p.o.o.s. stand for p. for pufs o. for of o. for oxygen and s. for slime. pufs of oxygen slime asked joe yup said the p.o.o.s.. the p.o.o.s. and joe kept on walking and they got hungry so they picked fruit and ate the fruit. when they got thirsty they would squeese the fruit and get juice. when they finished eating they went on. sudenly another p.o.o.s. came. this time it was stronger. it kept on spiting tornados at joe. joe kept dodgeing the tornados and going forward and then was joe about to smack right into him when he moved up and dodged it then joe’s p.o.o.s. was right behind him then joes p.o.o.s. tacled the wild p.o.o.s. then joe sucked up the p.o.o.s. and all the tornados went out then joe did not tame it but used its power then the joe’s p.o.o.s. grew legs. legs shouted the p.o.o.s. they are wonderfull thanks so much. that is what friends are for said joe.</p>
<h4 id="page-14">Page 14</h4>
<p>they kept on going on till he saw a door. it said field two. it is locked said joe i saw a key when i beat the p.o.o.s. it must of been for this door said joe. let’s go get the key said joe. what should i call you asked joe? bob said the p.o.o.s. there is the key get it before it disapears yelled bob. joe ran as fast as he could and got the key. the walked to the door on the way joe asked so is your real name bob? no answered the p.o.o.s. i do not have a real name. i want you to call me bob because i like the name bob. then they saw the door. thew went inside there was a huge hill right in front of them they started climbing. field two is on the other side of the hill said joe. they kept on climbing till they got to the other side. it looked like a desert! it was a little diferent. It had nothing living in it except bob and joe. sudenly through a pipe about ten feet away from where joe came from a catterpiller that went in the short path and tried to beat the master but he could not even scrach the master so he escaped in a door behind the master. he he came to the place where short path and the long path met. the other catterpillar dashed at joe. joe shot fire bombs from his tail. noone knew joe could do this not even joe intill now. to bad the other catterpiller died said joe. he did not die said bob he was defeated. i think you got those fireballs because you gave me legs and did not get something for yourself. and by the way where did the other catterpiller go asked joe. he is at his home said bob. he can start over if he wants.</p>
<h4 id="page-24">Page 24</h4>
<p>look said joe it is the key to field three. and look said bob a silver fruit. come on joe it says i bet you to eat me. i will eat it said joe. then joe ate it. i am metel all over said joe now if a person tried to smush me they would not be able to said joe. they went on then joe said i am feeling hot i am happy that i took some spare fruit so now we can squeese the fruit and get juise. sudenly they heard something the p.o.o.s. look and saw a very strong moster. i hope you know the weakness of this monster joe. i do not know the weakness of this monster but i know what the monster is called a mooc. then the mooc was distroed its weakness is to say its name out aloud to it. then the mooc went up to joe and said you beat me i shall come with you. they went on then a whole heard of mook came then joe’s mook coverd his ears then joe and bob kept on saying mooc til the whole herd was defeated. the p.o.o.s. got spikes on his back and joe could spin spiderwebs.</p>
<h4 id="page-31">Page 31</h4>
<p>then they went on then they saw something it was burly it’s a monster useing blury efect said joe. then bob yelled haiya then the p.o.o.s. faced his spiky back at the monster. it went right throuh the monster’s armor the monster was distroyd. then the monster came up to joe, bob and the mooc and said you beat me i will come with you not! calm down p.o.o.s. we will soon beat him in his strong form. they kept going. then they saw the door to field three they tried to fit the key in but it would not fit. then the p.o.o.s. yelled that is the key to the master! now we have to go back and get the key said joe. then they started going back then another mook came joe’s mooc just coverd his ears and said mooc then the wild mooc was distroyd. then another mooc came. joe’s mooc did the same thing and the wild mooc was distroyd. then they came to the door to field two.</p>
<h4 id="page-37">Page 37</h4>
<p>they went into field one. then they saw something flying around then it landed and it was a flying apatasaurus! then from its tail chuncks of ice at joe. joe doged them and became steel. then joe shot fire bombs at the flying apatasaurus and sinse fire melts ice the flying apatasaurus was beaten. then the flying apatasaurus went up to joe and said you beat me now i am on your team. then they got to the door to adventure. they got the key to field three and went back to the door to field two but on the way they found another flying apatasaurus. joe used his fire bombs at it and it was distroyed. they went on. then they saw a fruit that was just like the metal fruit exept it was fiery instead of shiny. joe ate it and became fiery. then they came to the door to field two. they went inside. then a big monster jumped up and said i am the desert montor. i devoer elephants and you are a mere catterpiller! then joe said i am not mere and i have gained a lot and will beat you. then the flying apatasaurus wacked the desert monster and stepped on it. then the desert monster went up to joe and siad you beat me i will now come on your team. soon joe saw another desert monster. then joe’s desert monster held hands with the wild desert monster and flung it to the ground. then they got to the door to field three.</p>
<h4 id="page-47">Page 47.</h4>
<p>they went in. it was a vast ocean. the two strange things were first of all the water wasn’t crashing through the doors. second of all when they looked in there was lots of fishes but when they went in they all swam away. then the caterpillar that joe defeated came and joe asked what’s your name? bob said the other caterpillar hey! said joe you are my twin broter and the master monster used his magic to seperate us. let’s beat the master monster together and since my p.o.o.s.’s name is bob I will call you bro. at that moment a zooming shark zoomed at joe. joe spun a web and caught the shark. then joe shot fire bombs at the shark. the shark was defeated. then the shark went on joe’s team and swam joe team to the door that leads to the master. then the shark told joe he could fly on land. they went in.</p>
<h4 id="page-53">Page 53</h4>
<p>it was like a gigantic rock box. when they went in the door was sealed! they were traped! the master shot fire at joe. joe turned into steell so the fire wouldn’t harm him. then the fire turned into a net. then joe turned into fire and burned the net. by that time all of joe’s friends exept for his bro were burnt. then the master used distruction beam on joe. then joe’s bro went in front of joe and was defeated. then joe found out that the master’s life was stored in his asistant so joe used his firebombs on the asistant and beat it. bye bye master. then everyone was healed. then joe spun a cacoon and because of his speed he came out right away as a butterfly. then joe and his team went home.</p>
<h4 id="the-end">THE END</h4>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
