<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Origami on Varun Mangalick</title>
    <link>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Origami on Varun Mangalick</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 09:57:30 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://example.org/hobbies/origami/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Origami design: simple sauropod</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/post-3-dino/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 09:57:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/post-3-dino/</guid>
      <description>My third origami design was the simple sauropod (pics at more angles on the insta). If you want to fold this, the crease pattern is below.
Here, like with the lizard, I started with a tree diagram and did circle packing through box pleating. In this case, I found I wasn&amp;rsquo;t quite able to pack box pleating squares sufficiently, so I used a technique called the Pythagorean stretch which is what creates the strange polygonal areas in the pattern.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/dino.jpg" type="" alt="My third origami design - the simple sauropod"  /></p>
<p>My third origami design was the simple sauropod (pics at more angles on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/varun_origami/">the insta</a>). If you want to fold this, the crease pattern is below.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/dino_pattern.png" type="" alt="Origami dino crease pattern"  /></p>
<p>Here, like with the lizard, I started with a tree diagram and did circle packing through box pleating. In this case, I found I wasn&rsquo;t quite able to pack box pleating squares sufficiently, so I used a technique called <a href="https://abrashiorigami.com/pythagorean-stretch-advanced-topic-no-1/">the Pythagorean stretch</a> which is what creates the strange polygonal areas in the pattern. These do add some folding difficulty, but not as much as fully eschewing box pleating.</p>
<p>This model in particular made me think about how origami design fundamentally consists of 2 stages: base design and shaping. When designing a base, you&rsquo;re mostly thinking about what flaps of paper of what lengths will be present where on the model. Shaping is where you then make small changes to those flaps to make them look more like legs or antennae or heads. Often, the design process focuses more on base design, as this is the more systematic/mathematical portion. Shaping is more about artistry, and is often modified by folder to match their own vision.</p>
<p>Both of my previous designs were very minimally shaped past the base design, and this was mostly true for this one as well. I did find that there was enough paper in the back to open it up and lend a 3d quality to the model. However, one other person who folded my design ended up choosing to keep the model more 2d and add much more details in shaping, aided by using a much larger sheet of paper:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/dino_example.jpg" type="" alt="Origami dino example fold"  /></p>
<p>This was a great demonstration of how fruitful shaping can be, and how much potential there can be in even a relatively simple base like the one I created!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Origami design: baby sea turtle</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/post-2-turtle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Nov 2021 15:46:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/post-2-turtle/</guid>
      <description>The baby sea turtle was my second origami design. If you want to fold this, the crease pattern is below.
In this case, instead of starting with circle packing, I started by making the pleats I eventually wanted to end up on the back of the shell, then just played around until I felt the head and legs looked about right. For help folding, I made an album with pictures at various stages.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/turtle.jpg" type="" alt="My second origami design - the baby sea turtle"  /></p>
<p>The baby sea turtle was my second origami design. If you want to fold this, the crease pattern is below.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/turtle_pattern.png" type="" alt="Origami turtle crease pattern"  /></p>
<p>In this case, instead of starting with circle packing, I started by making the pleats I eventually wanted to end up on the back of the shell, then just played around until I felt the head and legs looked about right. For help folding, I made <a href="https://photos.app.goo.gl/9A7B7yotWEp5mnS86">an album</a> with pictures at various stages.</p>
<p>Like with the lizard, multiple people folded the design after I posted it!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/turtle_examples.jpg" type="" alt="Origami turtle example folds"  /></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Origami design: simple lizard</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/post-1-lizard/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Oct 2021 20:30:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/post-1-lizard/</guid>
      <description>The simple lizard was my first origami design! If you want to fold this, the crease pattern is below.
Most origami design starts with creating a tree structure representing the rough shape of your final figure. Then, you covert terminal nodes in the tree into circles to pack into the square, with each circle corresponding to a spike as long as the circle&amp;rsquo;s radius in the final design. In this case, the final model looks basically the same as the tree diagram, so we can jump right to the circle packing:</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/lizard.jpg" type="" alt="My first origami design - the simple lizard"  /></p>
<p>The simple lizard was my first origami design! If you want to fold this, the crease pattern is below.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/lizard_pattern.png" type="" alt="Origami lizard crease pattern"  /></p>
<p>Most origami design starts with creating a tree structure representing the rough shape of your final figure. Then, you covert terminal nodes in the tree into circles to pack into the square, with each circle corresponding to a spike as long as the circle&rsquo;s radius in the final design. In this case, the final model looks basically the same as the tree diagram, so we can jump right to the circle packing:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/lizard_packing.jpg" type="" alt="Origami lizard circle packing"  /></p>
<p>This is an example of box pleating design, in which you sacrifice optimal circle packing in exchange for easier foldability. Instead of packing circles, you pack squares, which makes sure that all resulting folds end up at 45 or 90 degree angles relative to each other. The few folds on the diagram which are not at these angles are shaping folds for small extra details like narrowing the toes and tail.</p>
<p>Here are pics of the steps of the folding process:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/lizard_steps.jpg" type="" alt="Origami lizard folding steps"  /></p>
<p>Excitingly, after posting the design, I actually got a few messages from people who folded it!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/lizard_examples.jpg" type="" alt="Origami lizard example folds"  /></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
