<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Hobbies on Varun Mangalick</title>
    <link>http://example.org/hobbies/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hobbies on Varun Mangalick</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 20:16:25 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://example.org/hobbies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Painting</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 20:16:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/painting/</guid>
      <description>Painting is something I&amp;rsquo;ve enjoyed here and there for quite a while. My first fond memory of doing so was in 8th grade art class when our assignment was to paint a sports scene for a sport we played in a pop art style. Taking pride in my lack of athleticism, I chose a picture of a guy getting hit in the face with a baseball. To my surprise, my art teacher actually liked my painting and selected it to put on the wall near the student lockers.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Painting is something I&rsquo;ve enjoyed here and there for quite a while. My first fond memory of doing so was in 8th grade art class when our assignment was to paint a sports scene for a sport we played in a pop art style. Taking pride in my lack of athleticism, I chose a picture of a guy getting hit in the face with a baseball. To my surprise, my art teacher actually liked my painting and selected it to put on the wall near the student lockers. To my greater surprise, it remained there years later when I visited again during high school. To my even greater surprise, it&rsquo;s still available on the <a href="https://www.artsonia.com/museum/art.asp?id=13942099">school&rsquo;s art portfolio website</a>!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/painting/ball.jpg" type="" alt="Man hit in the face painting"  /></p>
<p>Since then, I&rsquo;ve painted a few things on my own and most recently, I&rsquo;ve had a bunch of paint nights with friends to build up a paint wall in my apartment. All detailed in posts below!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jul 2022 13:42:16 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/writing/</guid>
      <description>What I was a child (and now), I loved to talk and tell stories. As a way to redirect my energy, my parents and teachers encouraged me to write these stories down. When I was in kindergarten, I wrote my first stories, some of which I&amp;rsquo;ve found more recently, and they were indecipherable. One, however, was my magnum opus: The Caterpillar, the full text (and pictures) of which are preserved in a post below.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What I was a child (and now), I loved to talk and tell stories. As a way to redirect my energy, my parents and teachers encouraged me to write these stories down. When I was in kindergarten, I wrote my first stories, some of which I&rsquo;ve found more recently, and they were indecipherable. One, however, was my magnum opus: The Caterpillar, the full text (and pictures) of which are preserved in a post below.</p>
<p>In sixth grade, I decided I wanted to write a whole novel. It took me several years, and the end result wasn&rsquo;t particularly good, but I <em>did</em> finish it.</p>
<p>More recently, I&rsquo;ve tried writing a couple short stories which I&rsquo;m slightly happier with. All linked below!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Origami</title>
      <link>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 09:57:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/hobbies/origami/</guid>
      <description>This is a hobby I&amp;rsquo;ve been intereted in over two separate phases. I was first interested in early high school, during which I made a variety of simple models from Youtube videos, and more interestingly, experimented with folding a tiny crane using toothpicks instead of my fingers.
I revisited this hobby during the covid lockdown, and ended up being sucked into it from around January 2021 to February 2022. During this time, I made an instagram account to document my folds.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is a hobby I&rsquo;ve been intereted in over two separate phases. I was first interested in early high school, during which I made a variety of simple models from Youtube videos, and more interestingly, experimented with folding a tiny crane using toothpicks instead of my fingers.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/tiny_crane.jpg" type="" alt="Tiny paper crane on ruler"  /></p>
<p>I revisited this hobby during the covid lockdown, and ended up being sucked into it from around January 2021 to February 2022. During this time, I made <a href="https://www.instagram.com/varun_origami/">an instagram account</a> to document my folds. This was a great way to engage more with other folders and keep track of everything I&rsquo;d made!</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/insta.png" type="" alt="Screenshot of origami instagram"  /></p>
<p>For anyone wondering how I got those nice white backdrops on my images, here&rsquo;s the setup (using a white poster board sheet):</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/origami/origami_photo.jpg" type="" alt="Origami photo backdrop setup"  /></p>
<p>I also experimented a bit with origami design, which involves a surprising amount of geometry. I read through <a href="https://langorigami.com/publication/origami-design-secrets-2nd-edition/">Robert Lang&rsquo;s book on the subject</a> and created three very simple box pleated designs (using <a href="https://bpstudio.abstreamace.com/">Box Pleating Studio</a>). Details on each present in posts below.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
